<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Janith's Blog</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://janithl.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://janithl.github.io/</id><updated>2016-12-31T21:24:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>One Last 2016 Post</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/12/one-last-2016-post/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-31T21:24:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-12-31:2016/12/one-last-2016-post/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;2016 has been... an &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; year. I've made friends, and I've lost some.
I got a lot of time to sit down and reflect, and I grow thankful every day for
the people who choose to stand by me despite all my shortcomings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of 2016, let me turn the things that made me happy this year into
a Top 5 list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;1. I got to travel&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since "the incident" of Feb 2014, I've not really travelled as much as I
would've normally liked to. This year though began with some travel: to
Pasikuda with the family. Places I got to travel to this year includes that
and our usual annual trips to Kandy, Anuradhapura (and Yapahuwa, a first for 
me), &lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/09/somawathiya-september-2016/"&gt;Somawathiya&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;Deep South&lt;/em&gt; (Katharagama, Mulkirigala etc.) and 
some really fun day trips Down South with the co-workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Deep South Instagrams" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/deep-south.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was particularly happy with the pics I got to take on the Deep South trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;2. I got to learn&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... both in and out of the classroom. In the classroom I tried to wrap my head
around ML techniques, &lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/and-so-it-began/"&gt;neural nets&lt;/a&gt;, advanced DBs and their ilk. Outside
of it, I got to play with React quite a bit, learn &lt;a href="https://laravel.com/"&gt;Laravel&lt;/a&gt; in a (cramped)
couple of months and push out live systems almost immediately (what a beautiful
framework, has changed the way I write PHP for the better). I got to dabble in
more Python than I ever got to. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got into &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCzZCiVjRPPDCpP5l7HIGRtA"&gt;some&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC3Wj9aO8VS5ZuXrtWfJf81w"&gt;crazy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCCOIcdii1bQmfSPHeNNw4Qw"&gt;YouTube channels&lt;/a&gt; that inspired me to pick 
up my guitar after years, adjust the truss rod and play some barre chords. I
followed Casey Neistat as he built and sold a company, and let John Green
teach me history like I was taking my AP exams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;3. I got time off&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got three months off to write my thesis' lit review, write this blog, &lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/09/the-unp-at-70/"&gt;write 
about the UNP&lt;/a&gt; and write code to buff up my Github profile. I started working
at YAMU the week after I was done with my final exam at uni, and I never got a 
proper break since. Those 3 months let me put everything in perspective and 
helped me decide what I really wanted to do with my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;4. I got bald&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, started balding. Not really fussed about it. (I feel that) I am well aware 
of my mortality, and that I'm no longer the youngest guy in the room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;5. I got to let go&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... of some important things which I once thought would stay with me for (most
of my) life. It was much easier than I thought and I feel much better for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is a stream and hanging on to a bank is not going to help when eventually
we all need to float away. Or so I feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Facebook Year in Review" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/fb-2016.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, that's been my year. It wasn't terrible personally by a long stretch, but
it was certainly challenging and 2017 promises to be even more so. I hope you've
all had a good year, and wish you all the best for the next one. Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>...</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/12/ellipsis/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-15T05:06:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-12-15:2016/12/ellipsis/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;විපතෙහි සැපතෙහි&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;නොසැළෙයි නොතැවෙයි&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;අටලෝ දම හුරු හෙළයා&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="people"></category><category term="sinhala"></category></entry><entry><title>දෙසැම්බර්</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/12/december/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-04T21:46:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-12-04:2016/12/december/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;ලියන්නද දේවල් නැත්තෙ, ලියන්න වචනනම් ගලන්නෙ හැබැයි ඉඩෝරෙට වතුර කැපුවාම 
කරාමෙන් එන වතුර බින්දු වගේ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ගියමාසෙ මම ලිව්වෙ design හුට පටයක් ගැන. එව්වනම් මොනාහරි කොරල ගොඩදාගන්න 
බැරියැ. 'ඒ සිඟිති ප්‍රශ්න ආයෙ දීපන්' කියල හිතෙනව මේ දවස් වල සීන් දැක්කහම.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;තමන් බොහොම අමාරුවෙන්, අවුරුදු ගානක් කැප කරල හදාගත්ත වටිනා බෙහෙත් ගහක් අවිදිමත් 
ඉදිකිරීමක් කරද්දි උගුල්ලලා දැම්මොත් දැනෙන්නෙ කොහොම වේදනාවක්ද? දුකක්ද? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;අර ගියපාර කිව්ව වගේ කිසිදෙයක් 'මමය මාගේය' කියල අල්ලගත්තොත් හැමදාටම ලෝකෙත් 
එක්ක ඕව ගැන කෙලගැනිලි.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ඉතිං අතෑරපං. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;නැත්තං &lt;em&gt;'දුක යනු...'&lt;/em&gt; කියල මීම් හද හද ඉන්න තමයි වෙන්නෙ. :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="මහනුවර වැල් බෝධිය" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/vel-bodhiya.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="work"></category><category term="sinhala"></category></entry><entry><title>November</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/11/november/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-07T07:35:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-11-07:2016/11/november/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;With any sufficiently complex system, a major overhaul always creates 
more problems than it solves; there's enough and more "case studies" of
the type you read about in &lt;em&gt;Software Engineering&lt;/em&gt; to back it up. Things 
that were fixed over years and countless late night hacking sessions and 
painstaking iterations break and you have to fix them again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wisest programmer I've ever met once said that software development 
at scale is all about &lt;em&gt;"letting go"&lt;/em&gt;. I won't say I'm anywhere near 
that level of Zen, but I'm certainly much less OCD about the giant fire 
in the room. It's a pointless to make reversing entropy your life's work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="This Is Fine" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/this-is-fine.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="work"></category></entry><entry><title>Listen To The Girl</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/10/listen-to-the-girl/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-27T20:40:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-10-27:2016/10/listen-to-the-girl/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So much going on right now, and all I want to do is run away and get a 
good night's sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5WKZ26Y_h7A" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</summary><category term="music"></category><category term="people"></category></entry><entry><title>අභය ලිබ්රේ වලට මාරු වීම</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/10/abhaya-libre/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-15T23:30:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-10-15:2016/10/abhaya-libre/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Abhaya Libre" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/abhaya-libre.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;දැං මේ බ්ලොග් එකේ අන්තර්ගතයට (සිංහල හා ලතින් අකුරු සඳහා) සම්පූර්ණයෙන්ම යොදාගන්නෙ 
අභය ලිබ්රේ අකුරු මුහුණතයි. ප්‍රවීන අකුරු මෝස්තර නිර්මාණ ශිල්පී පුෂ්පානන්ද ඒකනායක 
මහතාගේ  &lt;strong&gt;'එෆ් එම් අභය'&lt;/strong&gt; මුහුණතෙන් පරිණාමය වූ මෙය, ඒ මහතාගේ පූර්ණ සහය ඇතිව 
පැතුම් එගොඩවත්ත ප්‍රමුඛ මූනියක් සමූහයෙන් 
&lt;a href="https://github.com/mooniak/abhaya-libre-font"&gt;"සම්පූර්ණ නිදහස්, හිමිකමින් තොර, යුනිකෝඩ් අනුකූලතා පහසුකම සහිත"&lt;/a&gt; අකුරු 
මුහුණතක් විදිහට &lt;a href="https://fonts.google.com/specimen/Abhaya+Libre"&gt;Google Web Fonts නාමාවලියට එක් කරල තියෙනව&lt;/a&gt;. ඔබේ වෙබ් 
පිටුව සඳහාත් මෙය ලබාගන්න පුළුවන්. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Web Fonts පිටුවෙ කියන විදිහටනම් දැනටමත් අඩවි 1,131ක විතර 'අභය ලිබ්රේ' 
භාවිතා වෙනවලු.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;යාවත්කාලීන කිරීම:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;මේක මම ඊයෙ මහ රෑ නිදාගන්න කලින් ලියපු පෝස්ටුවක් නිසා වැදගත් කරුණු ටිකක් කියන්න බැරි
උනා.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;සිංහල වෙබ් අකුරු මුහුණතක් මෙතරම් වැදගත් වෙන්නෙ ඇයි?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Sinhala Not Rendering" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/sinhala-not-rendering.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;සිංහල යුනිකේත වෙබ් අඩවි කියවන අයෙක් නම් ඔයගොල්ලන්ට අනේක වාරයක් මේ වගේ තිර දැකල
පුරුදු ඇති. තමන් පාවිච්චි කරන පරිගණකෙ හරි මෘදුකාංගෙ හරි සිංහල ස්ථාපිත කරල නැතිකොට 
තමයි මේක වෙන්නෙ. සාමන්‍යයෙන් පරිගණකයක (වින්ඩෝස්, ඇපල් හෝ ලිනක්ස්) සිංහල 
අටෝගන්න එතරම් අමාරු නෑ, හැබැයි &lt;a href="http://blog.malinthe.com/2014/04/how-to-get-perfect-sinhala-text-on-android-4-4-kitkat/"&gt;ඇන්ඩ්‍රොයිඩ් වගේ පද්ධතියක "රූට්" කිරිලි වගේ ලොකු
ලොකු සෙල්ලං දාන්න වෙනව&lt;/a&gt; සිංහල දාගන්න. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;වෙබ් අකුරු මුහුණතක තියෙන අපූරුම දේ තමයි තමන්ගෙ යන්තරේට කිසිම දෙයක් අලුතෙන් 
අටවන්නෙ නැතුවම සිංහල පාවිච්චි කරන්න පුලුවන් වෙන එක. ඒ වගේම ඒ ඒ පද්ධතියට ආවේනික
මුහුණතින් පෙන්නන්නෙ නැතුව හැමතැනම (iOS වේවා, වින්ඩෝස් වේවා, ඇන්ඩ්‍රොයිඩ් වේවා) 
එකම් සම්මත අකුරු මුහුණතකින්  තමන්ගෙ වචන ටික දිස් වෙන එක.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Cross Platform" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/abhaya-libre-ios-android.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;මීට කලිනුත් ෆොන්ට් තිබ්බනෙ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ඔව්. &lt;strong&gt;"මලිති වෙබ්"&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;"ඉස්කෝල පොත"&lt;/strong&gt; වගේ ගොඩක් අකුරු මුහුණත් තිබ්බා. ඒත් 
ඒව එකක්වත්  "සම්පූර්ණ නිදහස්, හිමිකමින් තොර, යුනිකෝඩ් අනුකූලතා පහසුකම සහිත" කියන 
කාණ්ඩ තුනටම අයත් වුනේ නෑ. ඒ නිසා නිදහසේ පාවිච්චි කරන්න පුළුවන් web font එකක් සිංහල 
සඳහා තිබ්බෙ නෑ. මේක සිංහල අන්තර්ජාල භාවිතය කෙරෙහි බරපතල ප්‍රශ්නයක් බවට පත්වුනා.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;තව තොරතුරු තියෙනවද?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;මූනියක් සමූහයේ &lt;a href="http://blog.mooniak.com/"&gt;බ්ලොග් අඩවිය&lt;/a&gt; සහ &lt;a href="https://github.com/mooniak/"&gt;ගිට්හබ් පිටුව&lt;/a&gt; කියවල බලන්නකො. ලංකාවෙ
දැනට අකුරු මුහුණත් ක්‍ෂේත්‍රයේ අළුත් දෙයක් කරන නිර්මාණශීලී යොවුන් පිරිසක් විදිහට මොවුන්ව 
හඳුන්වන්න පුළුවන්.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="sinhala"></category><category term="design"></category></entry><entry><title>Octupdate</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/10/octupdate/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-15T11:51:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-10-15:2016/10/octupdate/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, I expected this deluge of werk werk werk to sweep me off my feet, 
but it has been pretty thoroughly overwhelming to get back in the 
saddle. In the last two weeks I have encountered highs and lows that 
staying at home comfortably cushioned me from for weeks, got food 
poisoning, and went back to my role as office plumber-in-chief. My god, 
&lt;strong&gt;so much plumbing&lt;/strong&gt;, and so much more to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Armoured Tuk" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/mal-working.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's so much (loud) activity in the office that Mal and I had to seek 
refuge downstairs to get work done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The traffic has gotten totes ridics now, you can't find a bus with seats 
at 1930 any more. Or hope to get home within the hour. Total &lt;em&gt;ඔබට 
සතුටුයිද දැන්&lt;/em&gt; situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And to top it off I had to go drink a buttermilk and it gave me the 
shits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such is life.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="work"></category><category term="biology"></category></entry><entry><title>Armoured Tuk</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/10/armoured-tuk/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-09T23:06:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-10-09:2016/10/armoured-tuk/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Armoured Tuk" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/armoured-tuk-indexed.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For &lt;a href="https://cerno.wordpress.com/2009/09/25/armoured-trishaw-book-banned/"&gt;Cerno&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="comics"></category><category term="conflict"></category></entry><entry><title>Me IRL</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/09/me-irl/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-27T11:30:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-09-27:2016/09/me-irl/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lightsaber Jan" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/lightsaber-jan.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Done using the usual process. Pencil on paper, inked with an Atlas 
Chooty Gel, and photographed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lightsaber Jan Drawing" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/lightsaber-jan-drawing.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's then cleaned up in GIMP, and traced into a vector in Inkscape, 
resulting in an outline:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lightsaber Jan Outline" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/lightsaber-jan-outline.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then reimported into GIMP, coloured, and highlights and shadows added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've done a Luke and switched from a blue lightsaber to a green one.
I've also forgotten to add the beard, and the legs look atrocious, but
such is life for a nooblet at drawing.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="design"></category><category term="comics"></category></entry><entry><title>3 Fictional Characters...</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/09/3-fictional-characters/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-26T21:37:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-09-26:2016/09/3-fictional-characters/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;...that are somehow supposed to describe your entire being. I saw the tag going
around. No one has tagged me, but when has that ever stopped me?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has proven to be much more difficult than I imagined, not because I don't
have fictional characters that I can relate to, but because...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, see, this is the thing. There are parts of yourself, character traits, 
that you like to think define you. These are all great and noble things, the 
Gryffindor of character traits, all golden and perfect. The naked truth,
though, is that that's what you &lt;em&gt;want to be&lt;/em&gt;, not really who you are in reality. 
When you do, in the sober light of day, do an honest assessment of things, you 
do fall desperately short in quite a few departments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhoo, after days of thinking about this, I finally got my three:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. Harrymort, &lt;a href="https://www.fanfiction.net/s/10677106/1/Seventh-Horcrux"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Seventh Horcrux&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear god, I really wanted to write about how much I &lt;strong&gt;absolutely LOVED&lt;/strong&gt; this 
fanfic. And I &lt;em&gt;despise&lt;/em&gt; fanfics as a rule. But please, guys, do yourselves a 
favour: get off that Pottermore trash and read &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt;. Pliss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Harrymort" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/harrymort.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, Harrymort is brilliant (and described by the author as "a series of bad 
decisions executed well"). He is remorseless and persistent, and did I mention 
brilliant? These are all character traits I tend to fanboy over, being so 
intelligent that even when you mess up, you've done such a good job of it that 
your failures are just as spectacular as when you win. They don't really 
describe me though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Evanesco troll," I murmured. The troll disappeared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hero worship filled my minion's Weasley eyes. "Wicked."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hermione asked, "Where did it go?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I shrugged. "Where does anything that's vanished go?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We stood there for a few minutes, contemplating the nature of nonexistence. At 
least that's what I was doing. I don't know about the children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, shortly after we all should have died horrible deaths via bludgeoning, 
the professors arrived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I do relate to a lot is his constant paranoia, and seeing conspiracies and 
intrigue everywhere (because if you're doing it, everyone else must be too, 
right?). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harrymort is so wrapped up in his lies that he starts to believe them, like his
absolute assertion that Hermione is a dark witch, Ron's a werewolf, and that
Muggle-born wizards and witches have been left behind by their magical parents 
with Muggles acting as childcare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I absolutely adore him. GO READ, NOW.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. Mark Brendanawicz, &lt;em&gt;Parks and Rec&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Parks and Rec" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/parks-and-rec.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Brendanawicz? More like Brendana-Quits!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why a character from the shows difficult beginnings? Why a really bland and 
unlovable character who didn't make an impact from a show full of strong and 
lovable characters?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After years of his life wasted in the city planning (a subject I deeply love) 
department, he finally quit to go work in the private sector. He makes silly 
decisions (Ann), breaks his legs, almost humiliates himself with by proposing 
to a woman who's about to break up with him, and leaves behind the people he
&lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; loved (Leslie). Despite all the crashing and burning, he was perhaps
one of the most realistic characters in a show full of superhumans. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They even threw out his plans for the park and got someone from Eagleton (!!) 
to redraw the thing. Such is life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. Max Fischer, &lt;em&gt;Rushmore&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Max Fischer" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/max-rosemary.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I, just like Max, like to think of myself as a grown-up and an intellectual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I, just like Max, am nothing of the sort. When you finally do meet an actual 
adult (like Rosemary - who Max sees as an &lt;em&gt;equal&lt;/em&gt; and a potential partner), your 
embarrassing childishness shows, you are incapable of processing how to handle 
a real relationship, and your Latin is terrible (or rather, &lt;em&gt;nonexistent&lt;/em&gt;, 
because you foolishly tried to get rid of it from the curriculum).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know, you and Herman deserve each other. You're both little children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we've all been Max at a point in our lives. When we realize that even at 
our best, we're still not &lt;em&gt;good enough&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="people"></category><category term="films"></category><category term="wes anderson"></category></entry><entry><title>Somawathiya, September 2016</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/09/somawathiya-september-2016/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-19T12:16:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-09-19:2016/09/somawathiya-september-2016/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Somawathiya" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/somawathiya.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shot in the early morning light.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="travel"></category></entry><entry><title>When You Say Nothing At All</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/09/when-you-say-nothing-at-all/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-15T06:28:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-09-15:2016/09/when-you-say-nothing-at-all/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Comic" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/wysnaa-comic.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not based on a true story (I hope?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;මෙහි එන සියළු නම් ගම් මනඃකල්පිතය.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="comics"></category><category term="people"></category></entry><entry><title>නිදහස් අධ්‍යාපනය ගැන අදහස් බිඳක්</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/09/thoughts-on-free-education-si/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-13T18:47:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-09-13:2016/09/thoughts-on-free-education-si/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="6 Percenters" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/6-percent.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;නිවේදනය:&lt;/strong&gt; මා ත්‍රිතීය අධ්‍යාපනය ලැබුවේ ශ්‍රී ලංකාවේ පෞද්ගලික විශ්වවිද්‍යාලයකිනි.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;අප ඉගෙනගන්නා කාලයේ (මීට වසර 5කට පමණ පෙර) පෞද්ගලික විශ්වවිද්‍යාල වලට &lt;em&gt;පක්‍ෂව&lt;/em&gt; 
වූ තර්ක නම්:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;උසස් පෙළ සමත් සෑම කෙනෙක් හටම රජයේ සරසවි වරම් ලැබෙන්නේ නැත. (2013 අධ්‍යයේන 
වර්ෂය තුළ, සුදුසුකම් ලත් සිසුන්ගෙන් බඳවාගෙන ඇත්තේ 16.5% ක් පමණි - විශ්වවිද්‍යාල ප්‍රතිපාදන 
කොමිෂන් සභාව)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ධනවත් පවුල් වල දරුවන් විදේශ ගතව සරසවි අධ්‍යාපනය ලබනු ඇත.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(මා වැනි) විදේශ ගතවීමට වත්කම් නැති අයට පිලිසරණට ඇත්තේ  පෞද්ගලික විශ්වවිද්‍යාල 
පමණි.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inter_University_Students%27_Federation"&gt;&lt;em&gt;අන්තරය&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; ජුගුප්සාජනකය.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;තර්කය සරලය, නිගමනය ඍජුය: &lt;strong&gt;පෞද්ගලික විශ්වවිද්‍යාලයන්ට ඉඩ ලබා දෙනු&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;කාලයාගේ ඇවෑමෙන් සියල්ල වෙනස් වේ. ලොව පුරා බොහෝ සිසුන් තම අධ්‍යාපනයට වැයවෙන 
මුදල පියවාගැනීමට නොහැකිව ශිෂ්‍ය ණය අර්බුද වලට මුහුණපාමින් සිටී. අධ්‍යාපනය වානිජකරණය 
සහ එහි ආදීනව ලෝකය පුරා කතාබහට ලක් වෙමින් ඇත.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;විශ්වවිද්‍යාල අධ්‍යාපනය සිසුන් හට ලබාදිය යුතු අයිතියක් යැයි මතයක් සමාජගතව ඇත. මමද මෙය
පිලිගනිමි. නමුත්:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;උසස් පෙළ සමත් සෑම කෙනෙක් හටම මෙම අවස්ථාව ලබා දිය යුතුය. මෙය 100%කටම පොදු 
අවස්ථාවක් මිස 16.5%කට සීමාවූ දෙයක් නොවිය යුතුය. z-score කඩ ඉමෙන් දශමෙකිනුත් 
පංගුවකින් සරසවි වරම් අහිමි වූවන් &lt;em&gt;අට පාස්&lt;/em&gt; ගණයට වට්ටන්නට වුවමනා නැත.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;මෙසේ 6 ගුණයකින් විශ්වවිද්‍යාල පද්ධතිය පුළුල් කිරීම සහ නඩත්තු කිරීම සඳහා දැවැන්ත පිරිවැයක් 
යෙදීමට සිදුවනු ඇත. මෙය ණය බරින් පීඩිත, ආදායම් බදු අයකරගැනීමෙහිලා දුර්වල ශ්‍රී ලංකාණ්ඩුව 
විසින්  තනිවම කරනු ඇතැයි බලාපොරොත්තු වීම බොළඳ කමකි. රජය හා  පෞද්ගලික අංශය හවුල් වී
මෙම මෙහෙවර කිරීමට සිදුවනු ඇත.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;අද රට තුළද, ජාත්‍යන්තරයේද අධ්‍යාපනය ඉතාමත් අධික වියදමකින් යුතු සේවාවකි. අපේ 
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C._W._W._Kannangara"&gt;කන්නන්ගර&lt;/a&gt; නිදහස් අධ්‍යාපනයේ වැදගත්ම අංගය වූයේ අන්ත දිළිඳු, අසරණ සිසුවෙකුට පවා 
ඉගෙනගෙන දියුණුවීමට තිබූ අවස්ථාවයි. එම අවස්ථාව රැකගැනීම අප සැමගේ පරම යුතුකමයි.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;යම් සේ තමන් සහ තම සහෝදරයන් ලබන්නාවූ අධ්‍යාපනය සඳහා ගෙවීමට වත්කම් ඇති සිසුන්හූද 
සිටිති. ඔවුන්ට හැකිසේ පද්ධතියට මූල්‍යමය ආධාර ලබා දිය හැකිය.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;සිසු ණය පහසුකම් ලබා දෙන අවස්ථා වලදී  &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/07/10/upshot/america-can-fix-its-student-loan-crisis-just-ask-australia.html"&gt;නැවත ගෙවීමේ කාලය වසර 25ක් - 30ක් අතර&lt;/a&gt; 
විය යුතුය.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet despite this widespread borrowing, there is no student debt 
crisis in Sweden, because payments are spread out over 25 years. They 
also start out low, rising slowly over time. [...] In Germany, students 
pay their loans over 20 years; in England, it’s 30 years. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes sense. A core principle of finance is that the length of 
debt payments should align with the life of the asset. We pay for cars 
over five years and homes over 30 years because homes last a lot longer 
than cars. An education pays off over a lifetime, so it makes sense that 
student loans should be paid off over a long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;මෙම ලිපිය කිසිසේත්ම &lt;strong&gt;මෙරට පෞද්ගලික විශ්වවිද්‍යාල අහෝසි කිරීමට පක්‍ෂපාතීව ලිවූවක් 
නොවේ&lt;/strong&gt;. නමුත්, අවැසි සිසුන්ට හොඳ පොදු  විශ්වවිද්‍යාල පද්ධතියකක් තෝරාගැනීමට හා එයට 
පිවිසීමේ අයිතිය තිබිය යුතුය.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;වර්තමානයේ රජයේ විශ්වවිද්‍යාලය තුළ විවිධ අර්බුද ඇත. ආචාර්යව්රුන්ගේ සිට අනද්‍යයන කාර්ය 
මණ්ඩලය දක්වා වූ වැටුප් අර්බුද, වැඩවර්ජන, නවක වදය, නව සොයාගැනීම් හා පර්යේෂණ
ප්‍රකාශනයට පත්කිරීමේ (research publications) ඇති දුර්වලතා, 
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intellectual_inbreeding"&gt;academic inbreeding&lt;/a&gt; හා මෙකී නොකී විවිධ ගණයේ ගැටළු සරසවි තුළ ඇත. රජයේ 
වෛද්‍ය නිලධාරී සංගමයේ ආත්මාර්ථකාමී ක්‍රියාකලාපය හා වෛද්‍ය සිසුන් එම වුවමනා ඉටු 
කරගැනීමේ අතකොලු බවට පත්කර ගැනීම සැබවින්ම පිළිකුල් සහගතයි.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;නමුත්, මේ රටේ ජනතාව මෙම ප්‍රශ්ණය සිහිනුවනින් විමසා විසඳාගත යුතුය. රටේ ත්‍රිතීය 
අධ්‍යාපනය ඉදිරියේ ඇති අභියෝග සහ ඒවායේ මූල හේතූන් හඳුනාගෙන ඒවාට ප්‍රතිකර්ම කිරීම 
අවැසිය. පෞද්ගලික අංශයට මෙය තනිවම කිරීමට නොහැක.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="uni"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="politics"></category><category term="sinhala"></category></entry><entry><title>The UNP at 70</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/09/the-unp-at-70/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-11T09:05:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-09-11:2016/09/the-unp-at-70/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Elephant" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/unp-elephant.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United National Party turned 70 this week. I thought I'd take a look at their electoral 
record, for funsies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data for this (short) analysis was sourced from Wikipedia. That data was in turn sourced 
from Department of Elections PDF files. I didn't cross-check the numbers because this is a 
blog and there is no accountability. &lt;code&gt;¯\_(ツ)_/¯&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll only be looking at General Election data because that's the only election that matters. :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Election&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="left"&gt;Leader*&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Valid Votes&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Votes Won&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;% Votes&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Total Seats&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Seats Won&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;% Seats&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="center"&gt;W/L&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1947&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;D. S. Senanayake&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,887,364&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;751,432&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;39.81&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;95&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;42&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;44.21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;W&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1952&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Dudley Senanayake&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2,327,626&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,026,005&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;44.08&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;95&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;54&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;56.84&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;W&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1956&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;John Kotelawala&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2,647,247&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;738,810&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;27.91&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;95&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;8.42&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;L&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;March 1960&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Dudley Senanayake&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3,041,420&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;909,043&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;29.89&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;151&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;33.11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;W&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;July 1960&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Dudley Senanayake&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3,076,869&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,144,166&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;37.19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;151&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;19.87&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;L&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1965&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Dudley Senanayake&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4,046,720&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,590,929&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;39.31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;151&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;66&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;43.71&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;W&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1970&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Dudley Senanayake&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4,991,798&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,892,525&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;37.91&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;151&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;11.26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;L&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1977&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;J. R. Jayewardene&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;6,243,573&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3,179,221&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;50.92&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;168&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;140&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;83.33&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;W&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1989&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;R. Premadasa&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5,596,468&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2,838,005&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;50.71&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;225&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;125&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;55.56&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;W&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1994&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;D. B. Wijetunga&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;7,943,706&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3,498,370&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;44.04&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;225&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;94&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;41.78&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;L&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Ranil Wickremesinghe&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;8,647,668&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3,477,770&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;40.22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;225&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;89&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;39.56&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;L&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2001&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Ranil Wickremesinghe&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;8,955,869&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4,086,026&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;45.62&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;225&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;109&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;48.44&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;W&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2004&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Ranil Wickremesinghe&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;9,262,732&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3,504,200&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;37.83&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;225&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;82&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;36.44&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;L&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Ranil Wickremesinghe&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;8,033,717&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2,357,057&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;29.34&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;225&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;60&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;26.67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;L&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="left"&gt;Ranil Wickremesinghe&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;11,166,975&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5,098,916&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;45.66&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;225&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;106&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;47.11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;W&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;win&lt;/em&gt; is when the UNP went on to form a government. This was sometimes done by forming 
coalitions (e.g. in 1965).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Some Descriptive Statistics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; df[&amp;#39;% Votes&amp;#39;].describe()
count    15.000000
mean     40.029333
std       7.121773
min      27.910000
25%      37.510000
50%      39.810000
75%      44.850000
max      50.920000
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On average the UNP won 40% of the vote, with a fairly low deviation from that 
norm. The percentage of seats it has won has varied wildly from 8.4% to 83.3% 
(in the infamous 1977 election), mostly thanks to the winner-takes-all craziness 
of the &lt;em&gt;First Past The Post&lt;/em&gt; electoral system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; df[&amp;#39;% Seats&amp;#39;].describe()
count    15.000000
mean     39.754000
std      18.945885
min       8.420000
25%      29.890000
50%      41.780000
75%      47.775000
max      83.330000
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Some Interesting Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sri Lanka, at least electorally, is not a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Two-party_system"&gt;two-party system&lt;/a&gt;. The UNP only won 
the majority of the popular vote on two occasions (1977 and 1989), and both under 
extraordinary circumstances. In 1977, the country was emerging from an unpopular 
experiment with a strictly-controlled, statist economy. The 1989 election was held 
during an extremely violent period of the country's history (more on that below).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="UNP Percentage of Valid Votes" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/percentage-valid-votes.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The percentage of the popular vote mattered little in the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First-past-the-post_voting"&gt;First Past The Post&lt;/a&gt;
system. The election was essentially a series of isolated local contests to win a 
particular electorate. It is even more surprising, then, to see that the UNP has only 
managed to win absolute majorities in only 3 of the 15 elections we looked at, and 
only twice under the FPTP system. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="UNP Percentage of Seats" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/percentage-seats.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ceylonese_parliamentary_election,_1947"&gt;1947 election&lt;/a&gt;, 29.11% of the popular vote and 21 (of 95) seats were won 
by independent candidates. One wonders how Sri Lankan electoral history would've evolved 
if &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proportional_representation"&gt;Proportional Representation&lt;/a&gt; was introduced during this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1977 remains the UNP's biggest electoral victory. The UNP won 50.92% of the 
popular vote and a 5/6th majority in parliament. The biggest win ever recorded (in terms 
of the popular vote) by any party though was &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sri_Lankan_parliamentary_election,_2010"&gt;6 years ago, by the UPFA led by Mahinda Rajapaksa&lt;/a&gt;, 
which managed to win 60.33% of the popular vote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two of the UNP's most celebrated leaders, J. R. Jayewardene and D. S. Senanayake, 
have both only led a single election each, winning comfortably. J. R. avoided having the election 
due for 1983 by sneakily &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sri_Lankan_national_referendum,_1982"&gt;holding a referendum to extend the term of the 1977 parliament&lt;/a&gt;. 
D. S. fell off a horse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;em&gt;leader&lt;/em&gt; becomes a bit muddled (like everything else) after the Executive
Presidency is created. In 1989, R. Premadasa was the leader of the UNP but wasn't running 
for the post of Prime Minister, and after the 1994 election Gamini Dissanayake went on 
to become the Leader of the Opposition (over Ranil Wickremesinghe, the previous UNP 
Prime Minister).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ranil Wickremesinghe has led the UNP at 5 General Elections, winning twice. If he leads 
the UNP at the next General Election, he'll surpass Dudley Senanayake (5 elections, 3 wins) 
as the UNP leader who's led at the most number of General Elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the First Past The Post era, the UNP frequently won the &lt;em&gt;plurality&lt;/em&gt; of the 
total vote, but lost the election thanks to the way electorates and the system was 
structured. Note the discrepancies between percentage votes and percentage seats, and 
the drastic reduction after Proportional Representation was introduced in the 80s:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Before PR:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Election&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;% Votes&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;% Seats&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;% Diff&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1947&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;39.81&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;44.21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4.40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1952&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;44.08&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;56.84&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;12.76&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1956&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;27.91&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;8.42&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;19.49&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;March 1960&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;29.89&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;33.11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;July 1960&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;37.19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;19.87&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;17.32&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1965&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;39.31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;43.71&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4.39&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1970&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;37.91&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;11.26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;26.65&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1977&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;50.92&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;83.33&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;32.41&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;After PR:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Election&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;% Votes&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;% Seats&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;% Diff&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1989&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;50.71&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;55.56&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4.84&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1994&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;44.04&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;41.78&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;40.22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;39.56&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.66&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2001&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;45.62&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;48.44&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.82&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2004&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;37.83&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;36.44&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.39&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;29.34&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;26.67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;45.66&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;47.11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.45&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Vote/Seat Diff" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/vote-seat-diff.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Vote Percentage vs Seat Percentage under different systems" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/votes-vs-seats-vs-system.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The number of valid votes increased from just under 2 million in 1947 to 11 million in 2015. 
The troughs of 1989 and 2010 are also interesting, because these elections took place under
extraordinary circumstances. In 1989, there was a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1987%E2%80%9389_JVP_insurrection"&gt;full-blown insurgency ravaging the south&lt;/a&gt;,
and 2010 was the year after the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eelam_War_IV"&gt;Sri Lankan Civil War&lt;/a&gt; was finally concluded. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Valid Vote Growth" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/valid-votes.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Swings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Election&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Vote Swing&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Seat Swing&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1952&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4.27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;12.63&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1956&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;-16.17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;-48.42&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;March 1960&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.98&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;24.69&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;July 1960&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;7.30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;-13.24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1965&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;23.84&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1970&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;-1.40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;-32.45&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1977&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;13.01&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;72.07&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1989&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;-0.21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;-27.77&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1994&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;-6.67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;-13.78&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;-3.82&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;-2.22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2001&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5.40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;8.88&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2004&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;-7.79&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;-12.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;-8.49&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;-9.77&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;16.32&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;20.44&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of vote swing (the different in percentage votes between the current and last election), 
the &lt;em&gt;'revolution'&lt;/em&gt; of 1956 was the UNP's biggest defeat, losing 16.17% of its previous vote share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the poor showing of 2010, 2015 was (surprisingly) the UNP's biggest gain yet, with a 16.32% 
increase. It edged out the 13.01% increase of 1977.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Vote Swing" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/vote-swing.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of seat swing (the different in percentage seats won between the current and last election), 
1956 was again the biggest loss (-48.42%). The UNP went from the 54 seats won in 1952 to a mere 8.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1977 was the biggest gain at 72.07%. The UNP went from having won 17 (of 151) seats in 1970, to 140 
(of 168) seats - J. R.'s infamous 5/6th majority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Seat Swing" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/seat-swing.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Data Viz&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making these graphs in &lt;a href="https://stanford.edu/~mwaskom/software/seaborn/"&gt;Seaborn&lt;/a&gt; took a helluva long time, mostly because I am incompetant. 
See, I even managed to misspell &lt;em&gt;incompetent&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the code for the vote/seat difference graph:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;matplotlib&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;mpl&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;matplotlib.pyplot&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;seaborn&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;pandas&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;read_csv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;unp.csv&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;set&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;style&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;whitegrid&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;font&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Georgia&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;plot&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;barplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Election&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Diff&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;forestgreen&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;plot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;get_xticklabels&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;set_rotation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;90&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;show&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And for the Vote Percentage graph:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;matplotlib&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;mpl&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;matplotlib.pyplot&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;seaborn&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;pandas&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;read_csv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;unp.csv&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;50 Percent&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;Valid Votes&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;Valid Votes&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;50&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;100 Percent&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;Valid Votes&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;Valid Votes&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;set&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;style&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;whitegrid&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;font&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Georgia&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Initialize the matplotlib figure&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ax&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;subplots&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;barplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;100 Percent&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Election&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;label&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Valid Votes&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;grey&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;barplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;50 Percent&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Election&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;label&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;50&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;% o&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;f Valid Votes&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;white&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;barplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;% Votes&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Election&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;label&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Percetage of Votes Won&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;forestgreen&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Add a legend and informative axis label&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;ax&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;legend&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ncol&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;loc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;upper right&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;frameon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="bp"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;ax&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;set&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ylabel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Election&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;xlabel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;UNP Share of Votes&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;despine&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;left&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="bp"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;bottom&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="bp"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;show&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And the vote and seat swing graphs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;matplotlib&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;mpl&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;matplotlib.pyplot&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;seaborn&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;pandas&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;read_csv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;unp.csv&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;set&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;style&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;whitegrid&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;font&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Georgia&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;swingVotes&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;% Votes&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;diff&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;swingSeats&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;% Seats&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;diff&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# replace swingSeats with swingVotes for vote swing graph&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;ax&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;barplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Election&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;swingSeats&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;forestgreen&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class="n"&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;show&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The data I used is in &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/janithl/ea79a2bd330e71f7a6ce6644927e152f"&gt;a publicly shared csv file&lt;/a&gt;. Consider everything MIT Licensed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
window.onload = function() {
   $('table').addClass('table table-bordered table-condensed'); 
}
&lt;/script&gt;</summary><category term="data"></category><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Sweet Lime?</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/09/sweet-lime/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-04T22:15:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-09-04:2016/09/sweet-lime/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Sweet Lime?" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/sweet-lime.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Sweet Lime?" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/sweet-lime-2.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much love for this film, and for Rita.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="films"></category><category term="wes anderson"></category><category term="design"></category></entry><entry><title>Thoughts On Free Education</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/09/thoughts-on-free-education/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-03T20:10:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-09-03:2016/09/thoughts-on-free-education/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="6 Percenters" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/6-percent.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; I did my undergraduate studies at a private fee-levying 
university in Sri Lanka.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above disclaimer reflects my natural sympathies in this fight. It 
was easy to support the private university cause, simply because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not everyone can get into state universities (in the academic year 
2013, only 16.5% of eligible students were afforded placements according 
to the UGC)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rich-enough will look for uni placements abroad&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The not-rich-enough-to-go-abroad (like me) would end up without any 
means to get tertiary education (if not for private universities)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inter_University_Students%27_Federation"&gt;&lt;em&gt;anthare&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; makes it hard not to hate them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple argument, simple logical conclusion: allow private universities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the entirety of my view on the argument, circa 2010 - 2014. At 
the time I was also strongly libertarian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it's 2016. The world has changed, and my views have matured and 
become more nuanced. &lt;s&gt;I have become a BernieBro&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's increasingly clear that student debt is a problem that does not go 
away, and that there are serious flaws with not only the financials, but 
the entire structure and role of tertiary education institutions. Are 
liberal arts worth teaching any longer? Is graduate employability and 
salaries the only measure of success for a programme?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I digress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My point is that I now think that tertiary education &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be 
considered a student right that should be provided for by the state, and 
that it should be available to all eligible students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am still 100% pro letting &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; eligible students get university 
education, &lt;strong&gt;not just 16.5%&lt;/strong&gt;. There would be no need for convoluted 
z-score schemes and the &lt;em&gt;anthare&lt;/em&gt; feeling all superior to people who 
lost out on admission by a fraction of a percentage point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not naive enough to assume the government will foot the bill for 
this 6-fold increase. A public-private partnership with scholarship 
funds etc. will need to be set up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am painfully aware, through my own experience and those of my peers, 
of just how mercenary a vast number of private educational institutions 
are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am also aware how expensive education is, and that not everyone can 
afford it. Poverty not standing in the way of opportunity, which is the 
greatest triumph of our &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C._W._W._Kannangara"&gt;Kannangara&lt;/a&gt; system, should be defended at 
all cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also plenty of kids who &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; afford to pitch in and pay a 
bit. They should be able to contribute and support their peers who 
can't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where applicable, student loans should have &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/07/10/upshot/america-can-fix-its-student-loan-crisis-just-ask-australia.html"&gt;25 - 30 year repayment 
periods&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet despite this widespread borrowing, there is no student debt 
crisis in Sweden, because payments are spread out over 25 years. They 
also start out low, rising slowly over time. [...] In Germany, students 
pay their loans over 20 years; in England, it’s 30 years. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes sense. A core principle of finance is that the length of 
debt payments should align with the life of the asset. We pay for cars 
over five years and homes over 30 years because homes last a lot longer 
than cars. An education pays off over a lifetime, so it makes sense that 
student loans should be paid off over a long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no need (nor is this an endorsement) to pre-emptively &lt;em&gt;ban&lt;/em&gt; all 
private universities, but a sufficient public option should exist for 
all interested students (which I wager is most of them).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are serious issues in the state university system right now (from 
under-paid lecturers, to strikes, to lack of research output, to 
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intellectual_inbreeding"&gt;academic inbreeding&lt;/a&gt;), and the GMOA's self-serving agenda (and using 
medical students as pawns to further that agenda) invokes nothing but 
disgust. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the people of this country should, for once, look at the core issues 
surrounding our tertiary education system and try to fix them at the 
root, instead of palming it off to the private sector and forgetting 
about it.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="uni"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Links: Machine Learning</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/links-machine-learning/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-25T21:13:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-25:2016/08/links-machine-learning/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm changing the format of the links posts to topic-based posts which I will 
add to over time. Seems like a better way to organize than basing them on dates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;August 2016&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://backchannel.com/an-exclusive-look-at-how-ai-and-machine-learning-work-at-apple-8dbfb131932b"&gt;&lt;em&gt;An exclusive inside look at how artificial intelligence and machine learning 
work at Apple&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fascinating look at how ML work is being done at Apple, and how it meshes 
with privacy of user data and the "Apple way" of absolute secrecy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple’s penchant for secrecy puts it at a disadvantage against competitors 
who encourage their star computer scientists to widely share research with the 
world. “Our practices tend to reinforce a natural selection bias — those who are 
interested in working as a team to deliver a great product versus those whose 
primary motivation is publishing,” says Federighi. If while improving an Apple 
product scientists happen to make breakthroughs in the field, that’s great. “But 
we are driven by a vision of the end result,” says Cue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://adeshpande3.github.io/adeshpande3.github.io/The-9-Deep-Learning-Papers-You-Need-To-Know-About.html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The 9 Deep Learning Papers You Need To Know About&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great overview of some recent breakthrough research in CNNs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...] a lot of the new and important developments in the field of computer 
vision and convolutional neural networks. [...] The first half of the list 
(AlexNet to ResNet) deals with advancements in general network architecture, 
while the second half is just a collection of interesting papers in other 
subareas. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/@ageitgey/machine-learning-is-fun-part-5-language-translation-with-deep-learning-and-the-magic-of-sequences-2ace0acca0aa"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Language Translation with Deep Learning and the Magic of Sequences&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The magic of sequence-to-sequence learning, taking a crack at the 'holy grail'
of Computational Lingustics: Machine Translation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we took two RNNs and hooked them up end-to-end? The first RNN could 
generate the encoding that represents a sentence. Then the second RNN could take 
that encoding and just do the same logic in reverse to decode the original 
sentence again [...] what if (and here’s the big idea!) we could train the 
second RNN to decode the sentence into Spanish instead of English?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With promising results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Machine learning researchers only invented this two years ago, but it’s 
already performing as well as statistical machine translation systems that took 
20 years to develop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And wider applications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About a year ago, researchers at Google showed that you can use 
sequence-to-sequence models to build AI bots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...] by replacing the first RNN with a Convolutional Neural Network [...] we 
can turn pictures into words (as long as we have lots and lots of training 
data)! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrej Karpathy expanded on these ideas to build a system capable of 
describing images in great detail by processing multiple regions of an image 
separately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://research.googleblog.com/2016/08/text-summarization-with-tensorflow.html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Text summarization with TensorFlow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish Google will stop stealing all our research topics. :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve observed that due to the nature of news headlines, the model can 
generate good headlines from reading just a few sentences from the beginning of 
the article. Although this task serves as a nice proof-of-concept, we started 
looking at more difficult datasets where reading the entire document is 
necessary to produce good summaries. In those tasks training from scratch with 
this model architecture does not do as well as some other techniques we’re 
researching, but it serves as a baseline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels like TensorFlow (and SyntaxNet) is really taking the NLP world by 
storm, especially looking at &lt;a href="https://research.googleblog.com/2016/08/acl-2016-research-at-google.html"&gt;Google's offerings at ACL 2016&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://code.facebook.com/posts/561187904071636/segmenting-and-refining-images-with-sharpmask/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Segmenting and refining images with SharpMask&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not wanting to be left out, Facebook has also released some incredible research
in the past few weeks, earlier with &lt;a href="https://research.facebook.com/blog/fasttext/"&gt;fastText&lt;/a&gt; and now extending to DeepMask 
and SharpMask:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DeepMask employs a fairly traditional feedforward deep network design. In such 
networks, with progressively deeper network stages information is more abstract 
and semantically meaningful. For example, early layers in a deep net might 
capture edges and blobs, while upper layers tend to capture more semantic 
concepts such as the presence of an animal's face or limbs. By design, these 
upper-layer features are computed at a fairly low spatial resolution (for both 
computational reasons and in order to be invariant to small shifts in pixel 
locations). This presents a problem for mask prediction: The upper layer 
features can be used to predict masks that capture the general shape on an 
object but fail to precisely capture object boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings us to SharpMask. SharpMask refines the output of DeepMask, 
generating higher-fidelity masks that more accurately delineate object 
boundaries. While DeepMask predicts coarse masks in a feedforward pass through 
the network, SharpMask reverses the flow of information in a deep network and 
refines the predictions made by DeepMask by using features from progressively 
earlier layers in the network. Think of it this way: To capture general object 
shape, you have to have a high-level understanding of what you are looking at 
(DeepMask), but to accurately place the boundaries you need to look back at 
lower-level features all the way down to the pixels (SharpMask). In essence, we 
aim to make use of information from all layers of a network, with minimal 
additional overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They've also done some work on real time (video) classification:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, our next challenge will be to apply these techniques to video, 
where objects are moving, interacting, and changing over time. We've already 
made some progress with computer vision techniques to watch videos and 
understand and classify what's in them in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="code"></category><category term="data"></category><category term="machine learning"></category></entry><entry><title>Quick poster I'd probably regret later</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/quick-poster-id-probably-regret-later/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-24T07:26:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-24:2016/08/quick-poster-id-probably-regret-later/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Sapiosexual" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/sapio-poster.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quick, dirty, and thrown together in a couple of minutes. NOT aimed at anyone
or any gender, okay? 😜&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brain vector by &lt;a href="https://thenounproject.com/term/brain/449421"&gt;Clockwise, via Noun Project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="people"></category><category term="sinhala"></category><category term="sexuality"></category><category term="design"></category></entry><entry><title>And So It Began</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/and-so-it-began/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-21T14:06:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-21:2016/08/and-so-it-began/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Backprop" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/backprop.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neural Networks exam in a week!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today's AA exam went much better than expected, given how little I studied for 
it. That kinda thing totally incentivises the wrong kind of behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What to do. I'll start with the (overdue) assignments and try to understand as
much of the &lt;em&gt;mind-boggling&lt;/em&gt; math as I can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And perhaps some day, I'd be able to do something cool like &lt;a href="http://science.sciencemag.org/content/353/6301/790"&gt;these guys&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reliable data on economic livelihoods remain scarce in the developing world, 
hampering efforts to study these outcomes and to design policies that improve 
them. Here we demonstrate an accurate, inexpensive, and scalable method for 
estimating consumption expenditure and asset wealth from high-resolution 
satellite imagery. Using survey and satellite data from five African 
countries—Nigeria, Tanzania, Uganda, Malawi, and Rwanda—we show how a 
convolutional neural network can be trained to identify image features that can 
explain up to 75% of the variation in local-level economic outcomes. Our method, 
which requires only publicly available data, could transform efforts to track 
and target poverty in developing countries. It also demonstrates how powerful 
machine learning techniques can be applied in a setting with limited training 
data, suggesting broad potential application across many scientific domains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="uni"></category></entry><entry><title>The Continuing Story of Bungalow Bill</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/the-continuing-story-of-bungalow-bill/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-20T15:58:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-20:2016/08/the-continuing-story-of-bungalow-bill/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Deep in the jungle where the mighty tiger lies&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bill and his elephants were taken by surprise&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So Captain Marvel zapped in right between the eyes, zap!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All the children sing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hey, Bungalow Bill&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What did you kill, Bungalow Bill?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hey, Bungalow Bill&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What did you kill, Bungalow Bill?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of all the messes that colonisers left their former colonies in, the mess 
created with the birth (and partitioning) of India is particularly sad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pakistan" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/pakistan-ethnic.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Durand_Line"&gt;Durand Line&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radcliffe_Line"&gt;Radcliffe Line&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="conflict"></category><category term="geopolitics"></category></entry><entry><title>Alan Moore on Conspiracy Theories</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/alan-moore/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-19T18:38:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-19:2016/08/alan-moore/</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main thing that I learned about conspiracy theory is that conspiracy 
theorists actually believe in a conspiracy because that is more comforting. The 
truth of the world is that it is chaotic. The truth is, that it is not the 
Jewish banking conspiracy or the grey aliens or the 12 foot reptiloids from 
another dimension that are in control. The truth is more frightening, nobody is 
in control. The world is rudderless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Alan_Moore"&gt;&lt;em&gt;"The Mindscape of Alan Moore" (2003)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="geopolitics"></category></entry><entry><title>කාලෙකින් හෙළ බසින්: චීන නිල මුද්‍රා</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/chinese-wax-seals/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-17T19:23:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-17:2016/08/chinese-wax-seals/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;අන්තිමට සිංහලෙන් පෝස්ටුවක් ලිව්ව කාලයක් මතක නෑ. ඇත්තටම කිව්වොත් 
&lt;a href="http://askubuntu.com/questions/459349/sinhala-unicode-wijesekara-keyboard-in-ibus-on-ubuntu-14-04-not-working"&gt;උබුන්ටු 16.04 දැම්මට පස්සෙ iBus එක හදාගත්තෙ&lt;/a&gt; අද.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;වෙනදටනං මොනාහරි බෙදාගන්න ලින්ක් එකක් හරි තියෙනවනෙ. අද එහෙම 
එකක් නෑ, හැබැයි පහුගිය දවසක reddit එකේ AskHistorians (ඉතිහාසඥයන්ගෙන් 
අසමු) සමූහයේ දැකපු අපූරු පෝස්ටුවක් ගැන කියන්නයි මම යන්නෙ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AskHistorians/comments/4xqfs0/how_were_wax_seals_and_such_not_counterfeited/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;How were wax seals and such not counterfeited?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;චීනය, ජපානය ඇතුළු පෙරදිග රටවල් වල අධිරාජ්‍යවරු භාවිත කරපු මේ නිල 
මුද්‍රා ව්‍යාජ ලෙස පිටපත් කරන්න තිබුනු ප්‍රධානම බාදකය මේවගෙ තියෙන 
තියුණු අඩුපාඩුකම්ලු. මීට හේතුව මේව අතින් නිර්මාණය වීමයි.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Han Imperial Seal" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/han-seal.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;හැබැයි පුදුමසහගතම දේ තමයි අද වෙන තුරුත් පෙරදිග ලෝකෙ එදිනෙදා කටයුතු 
වලට මේ මුද්‍රා භාවිත වෙනවලු. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even today, you can't sign a lease or buy a car/motorcycle or open a bank 
account without one (at least in Taiwan, Japan, Korea, with some exceptions). 
People mostly consider them more secure than a signature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;තව:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When selling a car or setting up a bank account, you need to not only stamp 
the papers, but also bring a paper from city hall certifying your stamp being 
legit (when you get a new stamp you bring it to city hall, so they have a kind 
of master copy).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;කවදාවත් වුවමනාවකට හරියට අත්සනක් ගහගන්න බැරි අපි වගේ අයටනම් මේක 
කියාපු විසඳුමක්.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="sinhala"></category></entry><entry><title>Thoughts on the "Silent Vigil"</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/silent-vigil/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-16T05:19:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-16:2016/08/silent-vigil/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There's been some &lt;a href="https://facebook.com/BBCSinhala/videos/677749315716153/"&gt;"anti-racist" vigil out of nowhere&lt;/a&gt; and there was, as 
usual, a confrontation with one of the "ultra-nationalist" orgs. Without writing 
any further about any of this, I will defer to the wisdom of the crowds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Vigil Comments" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/vigil-comments.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="conflict"></category><category term="people"></category><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Pairplots FTW! Links: August 15</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/links-august-15/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-15T20:06:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-15:2016/08/links-august-15/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Instalment 2 of the "sharing links" thingy. Shorter too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Software:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently subscribed to the Dataquest newsletter, and today got this post
emailed to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.dataquest.io/blog/python-vs-r/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Python vs R: head to head data analysis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make pairwise scatterplots: One common way to explore a dataset is to see how 
different columns correlate to others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Seaborn Pairplot" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/seaborn-pairplot.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above example is from the excellent &lt;a href="https://stanford.edu/~mwaskom/software/seaborn/generated/seaborn.pairplot.html"&gt;Seaborn Documentation&lt;/a&gt;. Good stuff!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Conflict:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read several great D. B. S. Jeyaraj articles in my ongoing fascination with
the Sri Lankan Civil War.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://dbsjeyaraj.com/dbsj/archives/1073"&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Pottu Amman” and the Intelligence Division of the LTTE&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was amazed at Pottu’s growth in later life and observed “I just don’t know 
how he is running the intelligence division so well nowadays”. But then academic 
brilliance is not a pre-requisite to run an intelligence outfit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is required is lateral thinking, practical approaches, devious cunning, 
organizational skills, shrewd judgement of men and matters and above all 
perpetual paranoia about everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://dbsjeyaraj.com/dbsj/archives/14588"&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Col Charles”: The ”tiger” Mastermind Behind LTTE Attacks Outside 
North-East&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was decided that Colombo should be taught a bitter lesson. Charles, then 
only nineteen was entrusted with the task. He moved into Colombo in January 1991 
and set two plans of attack in motion. Within a few weeks the LTTE struck in 
Colombo. The JOC headquarters was blown up. Ranjan Wijeratne was killed by a car 
bomb. This was only the beginning. Charles as an “unknown face” of the LTTE 
remained incognito in Colombo till 1997.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How inept was military intel at that time for this guy to lurk around for almost
7 years blowing shit up and not be noticed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Economics:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The excellent piece on the Daily FT by IPS Chairman Prof. Razeen Sally, titled 
&lt;a href="http://www.ft.lk/article/560914/ft"&gt;&lt;em&gt;"The Sri Lankan economy after regime change"&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First the Government hammers consumers with high prices through inflation and 
import taxes – which hits the poor particularly hard since they spend more of 
their disposable income on essential items. Then it bludgeons producers with 
price controls. This is market-busting, an echo of Mrs Bandaranaike’s command 
economy in the 1970s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the same old wine in new bottles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Old, established politicians have played musical chairs around the cabinet 
table, and kept a new generation of younger, competent professionals away from 
positions of power. This is not surprising: the old political elite – and their 
business cronies – have vested interests to defend. And so entrenched, 
unprofessional, bankrupt attitudes and methods persist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On tax reform:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objectives should be to get revenue up to 15-20% of GDP, while concurrently 
increasing incentives to save, invest, create jobs and boost productivity. The 
watchword should be “simplification”. There should be clean, simple rates for 
VAT and direct (personal and corporate) income taxes, with as few exemptions as 
possible. [...] Even relatively low tax rates will generate more revenue 
providing the system is clean, simple and well-enforced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the possible repercussions of this government failing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more malign scenario is that the present situation will spiral backwards. 
A macroeconomic crisis might be the catalyst. Or it could result from popular 
frustrations – no new investments, no new jobs, no change – boiling over. Then, 
in the Sinhala-Buddhist heartland, people might yearn again for a Big Man, a 
Rajapaksa or someone else, to ride in and clean house, sweeping away liberal 
rights and democratic niceties with his authoritarian broom. They could vent 
their frustrations at the minorities who got President Sirisena and a UNP-led 
Government elected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hat tip for &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/yudhanjaya"&gt;Yudhanjaya&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/himalkk"&gt;Himal&lt;/a&gt; for pointing me at this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been watching a LOT of "Crash Course World History", and I loved their 
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=alJaltUmrGo"&gt;&lt;em&gt;episode on Imperialism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, especially the oft-overlooked economic side of 
it. See also &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QfsfoFqsFk4"&gt;their episode on American Imperialism&lt;/a&gt;, mostly covering the 
Spanish-American War.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/alJaltUmrGo" 
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I guess not that much shorter. Oh well.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="conflict"></category><category term="data"></category><category term="geopolitics"></category></entry><entry><title>Links: August 14</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/links-august-14/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-14T17:53:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-14:2016/08/links-august-14/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/money/2014/10/21/357629765/when-women-stopped-coding"&gt;promised previously&lt;/a&gt; to use this space for link sharing as well, so here
goes the first instalment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Software:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gender disparity in computer science is an often discussed topic, and the 
following is one of my favourite graphs on the topic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/money/2014/10/21/357629765/when-women-stopped-coding"&gt;&lt;img alt="Women in CompSci" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/comp-sci-women.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I read about another study that confirms that software development 
is not the meritocracy it is often claimed to be. - &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2016/feb/12/women-considered-better-coders-hide-gender-github"&gt;"Women considered better 
coders – but only if they hide their gender"&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The researchers looked at approximately 3m pull requests submitted on GitHub, 
and found that code written by women was approved at a higher rate (78.6%) than 
code written by men (74.6%).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking for an explanation for this disparity, the researchers examined 
several different factors, such as whether women were making smaller changes 
to code (they were not) or whether women were outperforming men in only certain 
kinds of code (they were not). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was here that they made the disturbing discovery: women’s work was more 
likely to be accepted than men’s, unless “their gender is identifiable”, in 
which case the acceptance rate was worse than men’s. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the golden&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jenny Bryan, a professor of statistics at the University of British Columbia, 
uses GitHub as a teacher and developer in R, a programming language. Her profile 
makes clear that she is a woman, and she doesn’t believe that she’s been 
discriminated against due to her gender.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At the very most, men who don’t know me sometimes explain things to me that 
I likely understand better than they do,” she writes. “The men I interact with 
in the R community on GitHub know me and, if my genderhas any effect at all, I 
feel they go out of their way to support my efforts to learn and make more 
contributions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trust Githubbers to attempt mansplaining R to a Stats Prof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Machine Learning is a topic &lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/the-lastfm-dataset/"&gt;I am ostensibly interested in&lt;/a&gt;. This week, I
discovered a really cool &lt;a href="https://github.com/josephmisiti/awesome-machine-learning"&gt;awesome-style list with a ton of ML resources&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awesome Machine Learning Awesome: A curated list of awesome machine learning 
frameworks, libraries and software (by language).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A beautiful, beautiful tool and write-up by &lt;a href="http://www.martinoleary.com/"&gt;Dr. Martin O'Leary of Swansea 
University&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="http://mewo2.com/notes/terrain/"&gt;how to generate imaginary maps&lt;/a&gt; and a companion piece on 
&lt;a href="http://mewo2.com/notes/naming-language/"&gt;generating an imginary language to produce place names&lt;/a&gt;. Mind-blown twice: 
as a cartography nerd AND as someone who studied NLP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Imaginary Maps" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/imaginary-maps.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to make maps that look like something you'd find at the back of one 
of the cheap paperback fantasy novels of my youth. I always had a fascination 
with these imagined worlds, which were often much more interesting than 
whatever luke-warm sub-Tolkien tale they were attached to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Took me back to my childhood spent looking for, devouring and creating 
imaginary maps of my own. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Sports:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2016/08/08/sports/olympics/history-olympic-dominance-charts.html?_r=0"&gt;beautifully visual and data-rich NYT piece&lt;/a&gt; on how different countries
dominated different arenas of the Olympics over the years, and how certain 
blocks dominate certain sports. Part of their excellent Olympic coverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.espncricinfo.com/sri-lanka-v-australia-2016/content/story/1045673.html"&gt;Andrew Fernando's excellent write-up&lt;/a&gt; on the first day of the third test
between Australia and Sri Lanka at the SSC. He keeps churning out these 
exceptional gems that make me proud to be Sri Lankan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SSC ground happens to be in the clotted heart of Colombo's administrative 
district. Yet, although the Australia team may never set foot inside the 
National Identity Card Centre, which is a few minutes away, or the Ministry of 
Public Administration and Management, which is visible from the ground, they 
were on day one of this Test, given a thorough government-office treatment. 
They were made to wait for hours, run around, given brief hope, which was 
promptly crushed; they were sneered at, and mistreated, and by the end of the 
day, they were ready to tear their hair out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bureaucrat-in-chief for Sri Lanka was Dhananjaya de Silva, whose maiden Test 
hundred was a thing of superlative casualness. So unfazed was he by a scoreline 
of 26 for 5 at his arrival, he was like the civil servant who comes to work to 
find a queue stretching around the building outside his office, yet before work 
takes a long tea-and-biscuit break while chit-chatting to colleagues. He stood 
slouched at the crease all day, unfurling somnolent drives, and languid flicks 
to the leg side, appearing as if he was doing almost nothing. Meanwhile, 
Australia chased leather all over; patrons shunted from room to room to room 
in the building, all, in the end, for no tangible reward. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;swoons&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Conflict:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Col. Sylvester Perera's &lt;a href="https://globalecco.org/the-sri-lankan-civil-war-a-personal-reminiscence-col-sylvester-perera-sri-lankan-army"&gt;sobering account of the civil war in the 90s&lt;/a&gt;, and 
how lasting peace is yet to be achieved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Operation Riviresa was one of the major operations conducted by Sri Lanka's 
armed forces against the LTTE, and it was both well-planned and 
well-coordinated. The primary objective of the operation was the capture and 
liberation of the town of Jaffna and the rest of the Jaffna peninsula. 
By contrast, during Operation Sath Jaya to capture the LTTE stronghold of 
Kilinochchi, the country's political leadership overrode the advice of military 
commanders and drove the army to stretch its forces beyond the practical limits 
of defense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...] the intelligence provided to the military lacked answers to the vital 
questions of when, where, what, and how—the most fundamental aspects of a 
useful intelligence picture. As a result, our operations either were ineffective 
or became nightmares of shock and surprise for our troops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized that defeating an insurgency does not bring the conflict to a 
conclusive end. I had to put all my efforts into managing a post-conflict 
society for peace building, within a framework called disarmament, 
demobilization, and reintegration. Despite all our work, however, it seems 
that Sri Lanka is still facing these challenges [...]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D. B. S. Jeyaraj's article &lt;a href="http://dbsjeyaraj.com/dbsj/archives/47692"&gt;"Shelton Ranaraja: Principled Politician was 
Conscience-Keeper of the Nation"&lt;/a&gt; which contained some chilling excerpts 
from William Mcgowan's “Only man is Vile”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kandyan jungle seemed so at peace just after dawn on that October morning 
in 1989. In the twisted thicket of palms, bamboo and bougainvillea that 
blanketed the hotel, a handful of iridescent parrots screeched cheery greetings 
to the first rays of sun as they splintered into a forest of prisms through the 
morning dew [...] But we turned left that morning, and we hadn’t driven even a 
mile when we saw our first body–a headless corpse, hands bound behind its back, 
blocking the road like a fallen tree. A few hundred yards farther, there were 
three more, then two more, then four more, all with their heads neatly severed 
at the shoulders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Ranaraja expressed what I imagine a lot of people must've felt at that time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That night, in his modest home near the Temple of the Sacred Relic in downtown 
Kandy, one of the island’s parliamentarians spoke with quiet frustration of the 
trauma that this awful era has caused his island paradise and its 14 million 
people–“We wake up in the morning, and we know tomorrow will be worse than 
today”–and he tried to square the living death with the religion that had taught 
them from birth the sacredness of all life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re not to kill even an animal or an ant,” Shelton Ranaraja said that 
evening, his body shaken and broken from the horrors that abounded in the 
peaceful jungle around him. “I don’t understand why this is happening. I cannot 
explain it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So very glad I got to skip the 80s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, that was a long write (and read, sorry!). I should try to keep these shorter
from next time on.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="conflict"></category><category term="code"></category><category term="data"></category></entry><entry><title>Status Update: Mid-August</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/mid-august-update/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-11T20:23:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-11:2016/08/mid-august-update/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We are bound by all the rest&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Like the same phone number&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All the same friends&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And the same address&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I watched &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fr_6qMM_kU8"&gt;Casey Neistat repair a chair&lt;/a&gt; to get over the boredom of 
jury duty and having nothing productive to do all day. He got a 90 minute lunch 
break, and he. built. something. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kinda makes you feel useless when you waste whole days doing nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, I have been wasting days. That was what the whole &lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/thoughts-on-the-mind/"&gt;"loud accusations 
of betrayal directed at my mind" episode&lt;/a&gt; was about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been working on an &lt;a href="http://electron.atom.io/"&gt;Electron&lt;/a&gt; app on the side though, to get familiar 
with the thing. I like it so far, very neat and I get to use React and all the
rest of it. Will release the code on Github if it ever starts doing what I want 
it to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm working on an algorithms presentation for uni and freaking out right now. 
Progress has been slow and the availability of the internet hasn't been helping:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;         day         rx      |     tx      |    total    |   avg. rate
     ------------------------+-------------+-------------+---------------
     08/07/2016     2.33 GiB |  165.41 MiB |    2.49 GiB |  241.70 kbit/s
     08/08/2016     1.50 GiB |  155.75 MiB |    1.65 GiB |  159.95 kbit/s
     08/09/2016   691.81 MiB |   76.57 MiB |  768.38 MiB |   72.85 kbit/s
     08/10/2016     1.18 GiB |  117.25 MiB |    1.30 GiB |  125.89 kbit/s
     08/11/2016   763.70 MiB |   82.37 MiB |  846.07 MiB |  101.63 kbit/s
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I planned to make short posts on this blog with a bit of a longer submission 
statement (more than one quote, some thoughts added in) than Facebook whenever 
I wanted to share a link, but I haven't been using it in such a way. I should 
start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finishing off with a photo I took on the way back from Matara last week, on the
expressway. It was shot from a moving car, through a window with a filter on it,
and looks terrible in true colour. But grayscale saved it and it has become one
of my favourite shots of clouds I've ever taken, and I love taking pictures of
clouds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BIpGuozjQFV/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Clouds on the Expressway" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/bw-clouds.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="work"></category><category term="uni"></category><category term="casey neistat"></category></entry><entry><title>Allegory</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/allegory/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-09T21:43:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-09:2016/08/allegory/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have good friends who are drinkers. I have good friends who are social 
drinkers, but aren't really drinkers. I have good friends who aren't drinkers.
I have good friends who are drinkers, and also want all the non-drinkers to 
drink too. I have good friends who aren't drinkers and want to eradicate 
drinking, and maybe the drinkers too.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the longest time, there was no drinking. Then, in the cold climes up North,
alcohol was discovered. It became quickly popular in those wintry wastelands, 
and made human habitation bearable. It spread, as human ingenuity often does,
far and wide. It even made it down here, to the sunny South, where the juices 
and nectars had held sway, where the coconut was indeed &lt;em&gt;'King'&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the tropical Southerner, the harsh solution held no great attraction. And 
for the Northener who was now in paradise, it didn't really make sense to wear
fur coats or drink harsh vodka, either. And so, the hybrids happened. Mix a bit
of this, with a bit of that, swirl it around for a bit of divinity. Cocktails 
happened, Sangria happened. There was a perfect blend, and it felt right at 
home in the sun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is how drinking survived in the South for many years. And then came 
the days of speed, of flying machines and mighty ships, of postal services
that were but instant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the vodka rediscovered the Cocktail, and the Cocktail rediscovered the 
Vodka.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And said the Vodka, "What have you done to my pristine condition?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And said the Cocktail, "But is it not nature, for things to evolve and adapt?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"From the North hail I, and you better not corrupt what is pure."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so, with a huge marketing campaign too, the Vodka made its way into 
Southern bars again. The cotton sarong made way for the fur coat, and the 
centuries of Southern heritage made way for reverential aping of the North.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the once peaceful bonds of brotherhood between the drinker and the 
non-drinker were broken, and families that for centuries were united regardless
of such trivialities were suddenly at war. The merry sessions of &lt;em&gt;baila&lt;/em&gt; and 
dance made way for chavs running around starting brawls and breaking bottles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To drink a cocktail was to blaspheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To even associate with a non-drinker was discouraged, unless you were engaging
them to drag them to the bar and make them drinkers too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The non-drinkers felt threatened and reacted. Street corners were all suddenly 
filled with fruit juice stalls. The Coconut had to be respectfully addressed 
as "His &lt;em&gt;Majesty&lt;/em&gt;, the King of Coconuts". Or else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shandy was thrown at bar patrons. Things got real ugly on sidewalks right 
outside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Would our fathers ever have started drinking if they knew the Sangria was 
going to make way for the Vodka?" "Fur coats? In this weather? Would our 
grandmothers ever have let this happen?" "All these drunks do is start brawls! 
It encourages violence, you know?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"All they have is an irrational fear of Vodka and Whiskey!" "Once you've tasted
Lagavulin, can you ever go back? This is, and will always be, what drinking is
about". "Those coconuts are just bitter about how happy drinkers are!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'd think the world would grow closer, that the North and the South would 
finally just be directions on a map. But from here, it seems to me, the North
looks on gleefully as the South tears itself apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have good friends who are drinkers. I have good friends who are social 
drinkers, but aren't really drinkers. I have good friends who aren't drinkers.
I have good friends who are drinkers, and also want all the non-drinkers to 
drink too. I have good friends who aren't drinkers and want to eradicate 
drinking, and maybe the drinkers too.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you are a good friend of mine, you'd know that this post isn't about 
drinking at all.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="conflict"></category><category term="people"></category></entry><entry><title>Some Quick Thoughts: The Mind</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/thoughts-on-the-mind/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-09T07:15:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-09:2016/08/thoughts-on-the-mind/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The mind is a fascinating thing that is little understood and often ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We believe we have mastered it like we've mastered walking, or playing an 
instrument, or typing, or speech. But it is fundamentally uncontrollable and 
has a "mind of its own". Har har.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making the fundamental error of announcing your plans before you implement them
can cause your brain to reward you before you've accomplished anything, and 
therefore leads you to &lt;a href="http://berkeleysciencereview.com/when-telling-others-about-your-goals-compromises-them/"&gt;not accomplish those plans at all&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research conducted by Peter Gollwitzer has shown that individuals feel closer 
to having achieved their identity goals when their identity-relevant activities 
(e.g., attending medical school) are noticed by others. On the basis of this 
work, Gollwitzer and his colleagues hypothesized that even if others notice 
only our plans for identity-relevant activities, we might also feel closer to 
having achieved our identity goals. Because we then feel closer to having 
achieved our identity goals, we may feel less of a need to actually enact those 
behaviours&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm finding out first hand how frustrating this can be, at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="people"></category><category term="biology"></category></entry><entry><title>The month of Augustus</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/the-month-of-augustus/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-31T22:41:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-31:2016/07/the-month-of-augustus/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It begins tomorrow, and I'm really excited because I've been FUP'd by SLT for
the last few days. It's been painful going, as &lt;code&gt;vnstat&lt;/code&gt; attests:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;         day         rx      |     tx      |    total    |   avg. rate
     ------------------------+-------------+-------------+---------------
     07/22/2016   410.55 MiB |   54.48 MiB |  465.03 MiB |   44.09 kbit/s
     07/23/2016   231.05 MiB |   36.32 MiB |  267.37 MiB |   25.35 kbit/s
     07/24/2016   620.32 MiB |   84.95 MiB |  705.27 MiB |   66.87 kbit/s
     07/25/2016   413.00 MiB |   59.05 MiB |  472.05 MiB |   44.76 kbit/s
     07/26/2016   392.72 MiB |   60.14 MiB |  452.86 MiB |   42.94 kbit/s
     07/27/2016   401.44 MiB |   64.09 MiB |  465.52 MiB |   44.14 kbit/s
     07/28/2016   264.50 MiB |   25.76 MiB |  290.27 MiB |   27.52 kbit/s
     07/29/2016   312.83 MiB |   53.04 MiB |  365.88 MiB |   34.69 kbit/s
     07/30/2016   439.92 MiB |   45.89 MiB |  485.80 MiB |   46.06 kbit/s
     07/31/2016   134.91 MiB |   36.42 MiB |  171.32 MiB |   17.74 kbit/s
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been painfully made aware of how heavy Facebook is, when even scrolling
down the timeline for a minute or two and replying to a few messages can cost a
couple dozen MBs. Makes me wonder how I survived on those 1 GB limited SLT
connections back in the day. But back in the day developers cared about  making
their pages light, unlike now. Sigh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been making progress on my thesis (or its lit review, rather). About 3
more papers and I can forward it to my supervisor for a read-through, I feel.
Very much relieved that I've been able to get this far on things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Took a break from studies today (it &lt;em&gt;IS&lt;/em&gt; Sunday) to do some work on &lt;a href="https://github.com/janithl/Kottu2012"&gt;ol' 
Kottu&lt;/a&gt;. Things have been broken a bit since &lt;a href="https://blog.twitter.com/2015/hard-decisions-for-a-sustainable-platform"&gt;Twitter, true to form, 
deprecated useful functionality&lt;/a&gt;. So I got rid of the Twitter share counting,
recalibrated the popularity calculation, and - since I was in there already - 
moved the front-end to use Bootstrap. Because slapping Bootstrap on sites that
have worked perfectly without it is my thing. I'm hoping to deprecate the JQuery 
Mobile-based Kottu Mobile site in favour of the responsive Bootstrap main site 
in the near future, if there aren't any protests and self-immolations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Kottu Desktop" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/kottu-bootstrap-desktop.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Kottu Mobile" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/kottu-bootstrap-mobile.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code&gt;vnstat&lt;/code&gt; output since Aug 1 (this is why I can't have nice things):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;         day         rx      |     tx      |    total    |   avg. rate
     ------------------------+-------------+-------------+---------------
     08/01/2016     1.48 GiB |  133.97 MiB |    1.61 GiB |  156.10 kbit/s
     08/03/2016   305.62 MiB |   44.76 MiB |  350.39 MiB |   33.22 kbit/s
     08/04/2016     1.19 GiB |  115.37 MiB |    1.30 GiB |  126.38 kbit/s
     08/05/2016     1.71 GiB |  174.64 MiB |    1.88 GiB |  182.12 kbit/s
     08/06/2016   603.21 MiB |   53.36 MiB |  656.56 MiB |   62.51 kbit/s
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="code"></category><category term="uni"></category></entry><entry><title>July is the month of buses, and 2016 is the year of JS</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/busroutejs/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-22T08:32:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-22:2016/07/busroutejs/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, there I was, minding my own business, when Facebook 
"memories" or whatever threw this curveball at me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bus Route Anniversary" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/bus-route-anni.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out it was exactly 5 years ago that I hacked together 
&lt;a href="https://janithl.blogspot.com/2011/07/bus-route-finder.html"&gt;a small piece of PHP&lt;/a&gt;, with a &lt;em&gt;liberal&lt;/em&gt; amount of SQL logic 
thrown in, and it became sort of popular. We're talking a 
&lt;a href="https://github.com/janithl/Bus-Route-Finder"&gt;codebase&lt;/a&gt; like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;&amp;lt;?php&lt;/span&gt; 

&lt;span class="k"&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;find3Bus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$from&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$to&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;global&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$dbconn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$sql&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;SQL&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;SELECT s1.`bid` as busid1, s3.`bid` as busid2, s5.`bid` as busid3, &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;ch1.`changeid` as changeid1, ch2.`changeid` as changeid2, &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;(s2.`stopNo` - s1.`stopNo`) as dist1, &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;(s4.`stopNo` - s3.`stopNo`) as dist2, &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;(s6.`stopNo` - s5.`stopNo`) as dist3&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;FROM `changeover` AS ch1, `changeover` AS ch2, `stop` AS s1 INNER JOIN `stop` AS s2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;ON s1.`bid` = s2.`bid`&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;INNER JOIN `stop` AS s3&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;ON s2.`pid` = s3.`pid`&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;INNER JOIN `stop` AS s4&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;ON s3.`bid` = s4.`bid`&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;INNER JOIN `stop` AS s5&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;ON s4.`pid` = s5.`pid`&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;INNER JOIN `stop` AS s6&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;ON s5.`bid` = s6.`bid`  &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;WHERE s1.`pid` = :from AND s2.`pid` = ch1.`changeid` AND s4.`pid` = ch2.`changeid` &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;AND s6.`pid` = :to AND s2.`stopNo` &amp;gt; s1.`stopNo` AND s4.`stopNo` &amp;gt; s3.`stopNo` &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;AND s6.`stopNo` &amp;gt; s5.`stopNo` ORDER BY (dist1 + dist2 + dist3);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;SQL;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$res&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$dbconn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;query&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$sql&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;:from&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$from&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;:to&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$to&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$res&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$row&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$res&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;fetch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;())&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$row&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="cp"&gt;?&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="x"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yikes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this was hosted on a shitty &lt;a href="http://chavs.000a.biz"&gt;000a host&lt;/a&gt; that somehow 
still exists on the internet, and it looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bus Route Site Screenshot" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/bus-route-original.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And gave out results that looked like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bus Route Site Results" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/bus-route-original-results.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which somehow is better looking than anything I've managed since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;ANYWAY&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been wanting to rewrite &lt;a href="https://github.com/janithl/BusRouteJS/commit/eac72894410693c47426720e240a8d5719316b1b"&gt;this thing in JS since 2014&lt;/a&gt;, 
and I've been grappling with Dijkstra's algorithm for months 
over this. The moment of clarity was realising that bus routes 
&lt;em&gt;aren't graphs, they're linked lists&lt;/em&gt;, and using complicated 
graph algorithms is unnecessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Facebook reminder yesterday and having a &lt;em&gt;bit&lt;/em&gt; of free
time on my hands led to a 24-hour code sprint that produced
&lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/BusRouteJS/"&gt;this little thingy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; than the original, for example the same query
as the above Galle Face - Kottawa one gives a stupid result 
like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bus Route JS Results" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/bus-route-js-results.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data is ~ 5 years old and needs to be tweaked, and I think 
the algorithms can do with a lot of tweaking, but here it is 
and it runs 100% client-side. Yay 2016!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is this CRAP?!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update:&lt;/em&gt; The UI code is now completely React-based! All clean and 
beautiful. Yay!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Janith", I hear you say, "you go around the place talking about 
the how great React is and how important readable code is, and 
then you write crap UI code like this:"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;changes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;length&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nx"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;col-xs-12&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
        &lt;span class="nx"&gt;renderRoute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;distance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;routes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;routes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;changes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;length&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nx"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;col-xs-6&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
        &lt;span class="nx"&gt;renderRoute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;changes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;routes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;distance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;routes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;routes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
    &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;col-xs-6&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nx"&gt;renderRoute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;changes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;routes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;distance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;routes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;routes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
    &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;changes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;length&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nx"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;col-xs-4&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
        &lt;span class="nx"&gt;renderRoute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;changes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;routes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;distance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;routes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;routes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
    &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;col-xs-4&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nx"&gt;renderRoute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;changes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;changes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;routes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;distance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;routes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;routes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;col-xs-4&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nx"&gt;renderRoute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;changes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;routes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;distance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;routes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;routes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
    &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;index&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nx"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;panel panel-warning&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;panel-heading&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;h3 class=&amp;quot;panel-title&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
    &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;lt;span class=&amp;quot;glyphicon glyphicon-star&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt; Recommended Route&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;panel-body row&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
    &lt;span class="nx"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nx"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;panel panel-default&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;panel-body row&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Okay, I'm a hypocrite. I only had 24 hours to write this and I 
cut some corners. REACT TAKES LIKE &lt;strong&gt;6 HOURS&lt;/strong&gt; TO SET UP, OKAY? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm sorry. :C&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(It took a couple of days of hard toil to finally convert the UI 
code to React. I would never have made my self-imposed 24 hour 
deadline had I gone with React the first time.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why's half of router.js stolen code?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's face it, we all do this. Copy stuff &lt;em&gt;gedi pitin&lt;/em&gt; from 
StackOverflow. I just linked back to the sources, legal 
ramifications be damned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Is this bus thing the only good thing you've written? Are you flogging a dead horse?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wouldn't call it good, but yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What now?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've barely tested it, so I'll probably make some tweaks here 
and there. The code, as usual, is on &lt;a href="https://github.com/janithl/BusRouteJS"&gt;Github and MIT licensed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/BusRouteJS/"&gt;Go to this page, and it'll throw you not great bus route suggestions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="code"></category></entry><entry><title>The Lastfm Dataset</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/the-lastfm-dataset/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-20T09:09:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-20:2016/07/the-lastfm-dataset/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lastfm Reminder" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/todoist-lastfm.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Todoist reminding me that my Last.fm analysis is overdue&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I downloaded my &lt;a href="http://www.last.fm/user/JanithL"&gt;Last.fm scrobble data&lt;/a&gt; a week
or so back using &lt;a href="https://benjaminbenben.com/lastfm-to-csv/"&gt;this excellent online tool&lt;/a&gt;. 
It contains almost every song I listened to on my PC (and some from my phone 
and iPod) between March 2011 and November 2014, 12784 scrobbles in total.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will do a proper analysis &lt;em&gt;soon&lt;/em&gt; (sorry, Todoist), but here are some 
descriptive stats that &lt;a href="http://pandas.pydata.org/pandas-docs/stable/"&gt;Pandas&lt;/a&gt; 
throws out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;             Artist         Album         Title          Timestamp
count         12784         12593         12784              12784
unique          354           752          2048              12709
top     The Beatles  Past Masters  Sleeping Sun  09 Feb 2013 13:24
freq           1904           285            39                  8
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I want to do an analysis of how I discovered and fell in love with new bands 
over the course of these three years. I don't listen to music as much these 
days, but this is a good dataset and I promise not to let it go to waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; Added the frequencies and histograms for artists and song titles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Artists&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; df.Artist.value_counts()
The Beatles                        1904
Coldplay                            842
John Mayer                          604
Oasis                               499
Arctic Monkeys                      447
The Who                             345
The Rolling Stones                  318
Snow Patrol                         315
The Velvet Underground              297
Bob Marley &amp;amp; The Wailers            287
Noah and the Whale                  280
The Kooks                           246
Norah Jones                         211
The Kinks                           201
Badfinger                           189
Paul Simon                          179
The Jimi Hendrix Experience         160
Pink Floyd                          159
John Lennon                         146
Queen                               141
The Wailers                         140
Radiohead                           127
U2                                  121
Cream                               114
George Harrison                     111
Lorde                               100
Bee Gees                             97
Simon &amp;amp; Garfunkel                    92
Roy Orbison                          92
Billy Joel                           92
                                   ... 
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/images/artist-histogram.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Artist Histogram" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/artist-histogram.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Song Titles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; df.Title.value_counts()
Sleeping Sun                         39
Could You Be Loved                   38
Parachutes                           35
Stuck on the Puzzle                  34
You&amp;#39;ve Got to Hide Your Love Away    34
Word                                 34
Brothers &amp;amp; Sisters                   34
My Girl                              32
One Day                              32
Wild Thing                           32
Bigger Than My Body                  32
Junk of the Heart (Happy)            31
Stir It Up                           31
Blue Skies                           31
Day Tripper                          31
Don&amp;#39;t Look Back in Anger             30
No Woman No Cry                      30
For You (Shiver single Version)      30
All Around the World                 29
Strawberry Swing                     29
Lifeboats                            28
Let Me Go (acoustic)                 28
Ruby                                 28
Baby You&amp;#39;re a Rich Man               28
Bitter Sweet Symphony                28
In Repair                            27
Getting Better                       27
Rainy Day                            27
Love Is All Around                   27
Here Comes the Sun                   27
                                     ..
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/images/song-title-histogram.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Song Title Histogram" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/song-title-histogram.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="data"></category><category term="music"></category></entry><entry><title>On Unrequited Love</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/on-unrequited-love/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-20T07:45:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-20:2016/07/on-unrequited-love/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Boy oh boy, &lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/shes-wot-m8/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; is something 
I deal with quite often. I rarely have problems with people in my life, because 
I've learned to respect boundaries and not get involved in other people's shit.
But I hopelessly fail sometimes at keeping myself detached from people, and it 
leads to endless suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found this amazing &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Buddhism/comments/2psc9j/my_endless_struggle_with_unrequited_love/"&gt;/r/Buddhism thread&lt;/a&gt; 
this morning that was just perfect, as /r/Buddhism threads often are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout my adolescence and most of my young adulthood I never dated. I used
ideas about attachment and self-reliance as an excuse for not needing to, but
really I just stalled my own development and hurt myself by not finding an
acceptable outlet to express love and practice intimacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hah. So me. "Any relationship I get into will only lead to suffering and 
unskilled behaviour", and all that. The handful of times I've been &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; 
(stretching it, &lt;em&gt;talking&lt;/em&gt;-about-being-with more like) someone, I've been weighed 
down by immense feelings of, for the lack of a better word, Catholic guilt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little over a year ago I saw a girl and was immediately amazed and intrigued
by her. I had the feeling that she was a good friend from my childhood or
someone I had even known from infancy that I was separated from earlier my life.
I doubt this was the case, but it is just the feeling I had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've felt these sorts of connections too, almost sansaric. You find it hard to 
shake the feeling that you're &lt;em&gt;meant&lt;/em&gt; to be with this person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I'm not sure if it was my imagination but I think she had a small crush on
me too because of the way she made extended eye contact and smiled at me
sometimes. But as that happened, I started to feel like it was too good to be
true and I clammed up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aha, as is often the case. Be a douchebag and ignore the girls who take the 
time to talk to you, have no trouble perusing ones that don't give you the time
of day (not really, but the clamming up happens...).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few really good replies that take different approaches at looking at 
the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Buddhism/comments/2psc9j/my_endless_struggle_with_unrequited_love/cmzsv86?context=2"&gt;Altruistic Love&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are attached to someone, you want to be around them because of they 
make you feel good. You enjoy this feeling. It is pleasurable to be loved. What 
this person is to you is, essentially, an object of love. Attachment is about 
self-centered pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you love someone, you want them to experience happiness and pleasure. 
There is no thought of self. If you are the one they are attached to, then 
you want to be near them because it makes them feel good. It is about the giving 
of pleasure, not the receiving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've never seen love and pleasure described in this way before in a Buddhist 
context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people today believe you need a little bit of both. But, from a Buddhist 
perspective, you should love indiscriminately, without attachment to it. And so, 
when it goes away (because it &lt;strong&gt;WILL&lt;/strong&gt; go away... that is the nature of any 
&lt;em&gt;conditioned phenomena&lt;/em&gt;), you are not hurt. This was not about your own pleasure, 
and so you feel no loss. You are not torn from something that pleases you. 
Rather, you recognize that the pleasure that you could once give to this person, 
you no longer can. And that is fine. It is within the nature of a relationship 
for it to end, and so you move forward effortlessly, always giving love 
freely, never attached to it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've often felt that most of my human relationships (about 100% of them 
non-romantic) are about making the other party happy. Whale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Buddhism/comments/2psc9j/my_endless_struggle_with_unrequited_love/cmzpknj"&gt;Right View&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She's an impermanent, flawed person who pees, poops, farts and belches. Seriously, 
take time to visualize this (it's similar to an actual meditation that the Buddha 
taught, in fact he went more hardcore and asks you to imagine her as a decaying 
corpse...yeesh). She's not a goddess, she's human just like you. &lt;strong&gt;She's not the 
answer to your problems&lt;/strong&gt;, she is--and I think the Buddha would agree with this--
&lt;em&gt;just another bundle of problems&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Totally agree on the &lt;em&gt;bundle of problems&lt;/em&gt; bit, and the sort of work that goes into 
maintaining a relationship, and its downsides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you need to practice is a "Middle Way" of self-esteem. The Buddha taught 
that &lt;em&gt;to physically starve and torture yourself will not bring you enlightenment&lt;/em&gt;, 
but neither will pigging out and spoiling yourself with luxury. You need to find 
that middle ground of self-esteem where you believe in yourself enough that you 
feel you do have the power to achieve your goals, but not esteem yourself so much 
that you inflate your sense of self and become egotistical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big take-away for me here is the middle path and how as a layperson I should 
follow it. A lot of my guilt comes from how seeking a partner is basically seeking 
sensual pleasure, but I've never thought about the &lt;em&gt;starving&lt;/em&gt; aspect of it before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find peace and happiness within first, then see if you can relate to others from 
that place of strength first. Otherwise you're just like a druggie looking for a fix, 
not a human being looking to express compassion or true love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Buddhism/comments/2psc9j/my_endless_struggle_with_unrequited_love/cmzpip8"&gt;Pain, and Self-Compassion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best reply in the thread, IMO, came from someone who was "gay and grew up really 
devout Mormon, so I was closeted until the age of 22".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't think the purpose of Buddhist practice is to bring peace, per se. Peace 
is a biproduct of seeing clearly, and clear seeing and learning to stay with our 
emotions seems to me to be the purpose of Buddhist practice. One thing that helps 
me immensely is to see the relationships of close friends. All of them are filled 
with hard work, trials, and quite a bit of suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh god, yes. My rational half hates me for desiring something that I see is causing 
suffering for other people. It's like wanting to try Meth knowing full-well how bad 
it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took a long time for me to see that unrequited love lied to me. It told me 
that if only I could be with my roommate Adam, life would be perfect and beautiful, 
and I would be happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ultimate lie that love tries to sell us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what I also learned was that running away from the pain was not the answer. 
The pain of unrequited love itself contained its own solution. Meditating with the 
fundamental energy of it, I found an incredible tenderness in my pain. I realized 
that it came from years and years of living in the closet and rejecting myself, and 
that &lt;em&gt;the answer wasn't to find someone else to love me&lt;/em&gt;. It was to cultivate loving 
kindness and compassion for &lt;em&gt;myself&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't tried Metta meditation since I was in school, but I'll definitely give it 
a try after reading this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the deep pain still comes and goes--I'm not saying I've found a cure. The 
opposite. Buddhist practice has taught me that there is no cure. And that there's 
also no need for one :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm raw right now from a bit of a painful and sudden (like, this never happens... 
I felt like a teenager again) episode of obsessive affection for someone who 
doesn't even know I like her, and this thread helped me immensely. I hope it helps
you too.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="people"></category><category term="sexuality"></category></entry><entry><title>Thoughts on Turkey</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/thoughts-on-turkey/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-19T19:06:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-19:2016/07/thoughts-on-turkey/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been meaning to write something cohesive about my thoughts 
post-attempted coup in Turkey, instead of having a half-dozen 
status updates with cryptic captions that, when analysed together,
gives someone an idea of where I stand on the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://foreignpolicy.com/2016/07/18/turkey-and-nato-what-comes-next-is-messy-coup-erdogan-incirlik-air-base-nuclear-weapons/"&gt;Writing for Foreign Policy&lt;/a&gt;, 
retired American 4-star admiral and supreme NATO commander James 
Stavridis says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The highly unstable geopolitics of the Levant and NATO’s 
expanding security needs come together at a crossroads in Turkey. 
It is not only a nation, but a civilization as well, one that has 
an acute sense of its importance and history in the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ottoman Empire came to an end after the Great War, and the 
Turkish republic rose from its ashes - led by a man whose legacy 
has played a significant part of its landscape since: Mustafa Kemal 
Ataturk. Ataturk came to power in a defeated nation that was about 
to be partitioned among foreign powers, and led it on a path of 
modernisation that made it an important regional power and 
(long after his death) an important NATO member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is Ataturk's policies of secularism and democracy that the 
&lt;a href="http://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/the-purge-begins-in-turkey"&gt;Turkish Army vows to uphold whenever it takes power&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the Turkish republic was founded, in 1923, the county’s 
generals have imagined themselves the ultimate arbiters of its 
politics, stepping into power—sometimes savagely—whenever they 
felt the government had become either too leftist or too Islamic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether it succeeds or fails in this endeavour depends on who you're 
asking. For example, the biography of 1980s coup leader 
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kenan_Evren"&gt;Kenan Evren&lt;/a&gt; reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He professed great admiration for the founder of the Republic of 
Turkey, Mustafa Kemal Atatürk; however, he shut down many institutions 
founded by Atatürk and is often accused of deforming the country's 
legal system against Atatürk's principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Erdogan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recep Tayyip Erdogan was elected PM in 2003. His Justice and 
Development Party (AKP) embodies liberal economics and conservative 
social values. He was mayor of Istanbul (1994 - 1998) running on an 
Islamist platform, but was stripped of his office and imprisoned for 
"incitement to violence and religious or racial hatred". When he became 
PM in 2003, he was &lt;a href="http://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/the-purge-begins-in-turkey"&gt;hailed as some Islamist democrat messiah&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Erdoğan first became Prime Minister, in 2003, he was the Islamic world’s
great democratic hope, a leader of enormous vitality who would show the world
that an avowedly Islamist politician could lead a stable democracy and carry on
as a member of NATO, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erdogan's &lt;em&gt;"Neo-Ottomanism"&lt;/em&gt; and other policies are a fascinating discussion 
in and of themselves, but I'll leave those out of this post. What we need 
to understand though is that Erdogan does not trust the military to not 
topple him, which led in the late 2000s to a series of investigations and
trials pertaining to an alleged coup plan called "Operation Sledgehammer". 
From the earlier FP article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of senior admirals and generals were charged and jailed on suspect
charges in the so-called Sledgehammer scandals of the 2000s, and the seeds of
the current coup were planted when bitter military leaders watched their
commanders and mentors be taken to prison in handcuffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the evidence was &lt;a href="http://rodrik.typepad.com/dani_rodriks_weblog/2012/10/did-microsoft-steal-its-fonts-from-the-turkish-army.html"&gt;flimsy at best&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these documents carry last-saved dates from 2002-2003, appear to have 
been authored by officers on duty at the time, and were burned on CDs that 
were apparently finalized in March 2003.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet when forensic experts looked more closely at the document with a Hex 
editor, which shows all the binary information on the file, they made a 
discovery that revealed that the metadata had been tampered with.  In plain 
sight on the raw file was a reference to “Calibri,” a font that Microsoft 
introduced with Office 2007 as the new default font for Word, and was first 
released to the public in mid-2006.  The only explanation for this anachronistic 
reference was that the file had been worked on with Office 2007 before it was 
ultimately saved in an earlier version of Word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the aftermath of the coup attempt last week, there'll no doubt be more 
generals dragged away in chains, and more institutions falling under Erdogan's 
command in his mad rush for dictatorial powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this could lead to rocky times for NATO ahead. Of particular concern are 
the &lt;a href="http://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/the-h-bombs-in-turkey"&gt;nuclear weapons stored at Incirlik&lt;/a&gt;, 
70 miles from the Syrian border:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security concerns at Incirlik Airbase recently prompted a major upgrade of 
the perimeter fence that surrounds its nuclear-weapons storage area. Incirlik 
is about seventy miles from the Syrian border, and since last October American
aircraft and drones based there have been attacking ISIS forces. Its proximity
to rebel-controlled areas in Syria and the rash of terrorist acts in Turkey led
the Pentagon, a few months ago, to issue an “ordered departure” of all the
family members of American troops at Incirlik.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post came out shorter than expected, because I skipped the bit I really 
wanted to talk about - Erdogan and his politics. I'll hopefully have time 
&lt;em&gt;(lol)&lt;/em&gt; to write in more depth about what the last 13 years have looked like 
for Turkey under Erdogan, and what his potential endgame might be - for both 
Turkey and the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="conflict"></category><category term="geopolitics"></category></entry><entry><title>Where The Lovers Have No Name</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/where-the-lovers-have-no-name/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-18T11:06:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-18:2016/07/where-the-lovers-have-no-name/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Camouflaged Love by Prasad Aluthwattha" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/best-art-ever.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/aluthart/photos/a.1728487060739361.1073741828.1728099647444769/1732564683664932/"&gt;Camouflaged Love by Prasad Aluthwattha&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing I write can do justice to the artwork above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This probably pisses off so many radicals on all sides of Sri Lankan  society,
with their (very similar) views on sexuality and propriety. "Hoo!", I say  to
them, "Hoo!". Roll your morals and your bigotry and stuff it up your arse.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="conflict"></category><category term="prudishness"></category><category term="sexuality"></category></entry><entry><title>Saturdays</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/saturdays/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-16T19:18:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-16:2016/07/saturdays/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All alone, I have cried&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Silent tears full of pride&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In a world made of steel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Made of stone&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturdays are spent at uni, and whenever I'm at uni I think of a 
&lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/shes-wot-m8.html"&gt;particular person&lt;/a&gt; who 
has nothing whatsoever to even do with uni. At one critical 3 hour paper last
semester, I spent maybe  one and a half hours desperately stuck in an alternate
reality in which we were more than just casual acquaintances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uni takes a heavy toll on my brain as well. Just today, within a couple of
minutes of each other, I had to  grapple with Hopfield Nets, Boltzmann Machines
(and energy functions and my old friend - Bayes' theorem), Convolutional Neural
Networks and their various stages of convolution and max pooling, and - in a 
totally unrelated class - flow networks, max-flow min-cut, to graph colouring 
and its many fascinating applications (all the way from scheduling to Sudoku). 
The only prior exposure I had to any of this was knowing that 4 colours are 
enough to colour any map, because I'm a &lt;em&gt;cartonerd&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, geekery isn't the only reason I &lt;em&gt;enjoy&lt;/em&gt; Saturdays. I get to speak to 3 
peers (who are older and wiser, so not really peers) who give me a fresh 
perspective on a lot of things. This week's installment was on dealing with 
bosses and criticism, and how you need to put your head down and accept things 
as they are and not pick fights. I listened, and pondered, but I don't really 
agree - being the socialist and troublemaker that I am. I think bosses need to 
be smarter at this whole game (and more diplomatic) than their charges, and 
maybe get rid of the whole boss/employee thing altogether and see each other 
as partners (like &lt;em&gt;that'll&lt;/em&gt; ever happen in our deeply hierarchical society).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, an observation my aforementioned peers made a few weeks ago, and I can 
anecdotally confirm because a lot of my batch-mates who graduated with me ended 
up so, is that a significant segment of female Sri Lankan graduates never work
in that field - or work at all. Even in a highly lucrative area like Software
Engineering. They end up married, and apparently that piece of paper is a 
prerequisite. IDK. So the next time someone asks you why there are so few 
female programmers...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="uni"></category></entry><entry><title>Drift</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/drift/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-15T21:33:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-15:2016/07/drift/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Though I know I'll never lose affection&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For people and things that went before&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drift is only natural in human relationships, and you shouldn't really feel bad
about the inevitable. People change, relationships change, you meet new people,
you  move to greener pastures. It's perfectly normal to be mobile in a modern
society. I mean, what  are we? Serfs?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are people I used to spend hours with, at school, online, people with whom
I shared my life and my secrets. And whose secrets I kept. And all these years
later  we barely even keep in touch, which is normal, which is &lt;em&gt;fine&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if only there was a way to get rid of this pesky little thing called guilt.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="people"></category></entry><entry><title>Breathing</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/breathing/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-15T14:15:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-15:2016/07/breathing/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;'Cause I am hanging on every word you say&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And even if you don't want to speak tonight&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That's alright, alright with me...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today's been a bit of an off-day. In the last few days I've a couple of 
interesting Medium posts. Highlights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A healthy product company is, confusingly, one at odds with itself. 
There is a healthy part which is attempting to normalize and to create 
predictability, and there needs to be another part that is tasked with 
building something new that is going to disrupt and eventually destroy 
that normality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failure to create some form of predictability will result in chaos. 
Failure to create some well-maintained Barbaric chaos inside the company 
guarantees that a fast-moving, ambitious, risk-taking and ruthless someone 
else — someone outside the company will invade because they know what you 
forgot: hacking is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@rands/hacking-is-important-ea632819d87c#.5sr0fxo71"&gt;'Hacking is Important'&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve recently moved to a more “hip” location. We used to have personal 
desks, but now we have this “pick whatever spot is avaiable” open area. I 
dislike it a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@Svenskunganka/interviewing-my-mother-a-mainframe-cobol-programmer-c693d40d88f7#.7sslqjnn1"&gt;'Interviewing my mother, a mainframe COBOL programmer'&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Progress has been slow on the research papers I'm supposed to be reading, so 
I picked up watching (the 7th season, which I've missed so far, of) Archer 
instead. I will attempt, today, to print some slides and prepare for the 
lectures I have tomorrow. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I inadvertently opined on some work-related matters (&lt;em&gt;bad me&lt;/em&gt;) because I ran 
into my co-workers yesterday and we engaged in a bit of shop-talk. Whoops. I
just pointed at an &lt;a href="https://www.w3.org/Provider/Style/URI.html"&gt;old standard&lt;/a&gt; 
that I live by and hoped that it wasn't too intrusive of me to get involved. 
Again, &lt;em&gt;bad me&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mal B'day" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/mal-bday.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the reason we all met was: &lt;strong&gt;MALINTHE TURNED 26!&lt;/strong&gt; We're all getting 
really old now, eh? The thing was excellent, though Whight's other patrons 
might've not defined it as such, due to how &lt;em&gt;quiet&lt;/em&gt; our table was. Yes, 
we're always &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; people when we're together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That concludes my useless update for the day, stay tuned for more daily tripe.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="work"></category><category term="uni"></category></entry><entry><title>She's Wot M8?</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/shes-wot-m8/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-14T11:07:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-14:2016/07/shes-wot-m8/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why her though?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She's...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not your type? At all?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; my type, again?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not her&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Come on, dude. I've known you since we had other people wash our bums for us.
She's so not your type&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, we're grown-ups now. Shouldn't we look past "types" and all those
primitive constructs. I like her for who she is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Or you like her who who she makes you...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oh, you know. Saves you from your eternal fear of ending up with a... simpleton&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Look, you barely know her. In the past few days, from what I've seen, you've
been using that blank canvas to project your hopes and dreams&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude. Too much truth on a Monday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;She's your ticket to legitimacy, the girl who reads, and knows, and speaks
well. She's funny, and beautiful, and you know she's going to be on the top of
the world one day. The ultimate Manic Pixie Dream Girl for nerds who actually
want them to be a bit less dreamy and a bit less manic...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I ain't sayin' I'm a gold digger, but I ain't messin' with no...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Look, all I'm saying is that she deserves better than to be blank canvas, or a 
trophy, no? She deserves to be her own woman, and you need to start seeing any 
person you'll be with as an equal, not as a stepping stone for your own...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zip it, Sherlock. I think they've all stopped reading at this point...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ah, it seems so.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="conversations"></category></entry><entry><title>Status Update</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/status-update/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-13T20:56:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-13:2016/07/status-update/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was watching &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KlJnsHpWamU"&gt;one of the talks Casey Neistat gave at
Vidcon&lt;/a&gt; this year, and he talks
about his love for the 'act of creation', and how he loves his job just like  he
loves his family. The drive he has to wake up early to edit a video and put it
out, 365 days a year. It's crazy, and it makes me wish I had the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look, time for some straight talk, which I'm going to go into here because
nobody probably reads this (or knows it even exists). This &lt;em&gt;'sabbatical'&lt;/em&gt; was
going to be me getting down and slogging through a really difficult thesis, in
an area I barely understand (Natural Language Processing, Topic Detection and
Tracking, Temporal Text Mining etc.), and maybe rediscovering the spark, the
excitement that made me want to be a programmer all those years, and which
(along with a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i_2mWhfOhGU"&gt;swelling Oasis
soundtrack&lt;/a&gt;) drove me to create
some really cool side-projects while at uni that ultimately landed me the sweet
gig of being a developer at my current place of employment. And three days in, I
can tell you that motivation is running real low and a huge part of me wants to
step back from the challenge and go back to the mundane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Masters', which I started in Jan 2015, has been harder on me than anything
I've done before. Before, when I was in school or uni, I had 7 days a week and
all of my mindspace to understand what I was being taught and properly digest
it. Contrary to what people expect from me, I'm not a fast learner. I'm slow and
take my time to experiment and truly grasp a concept, before becoming so
familiar and comfortable with it that I can run circles around everyone else
with my newfound toy. Getting thrown toys (and frankly amazing ones at that,
like R or NLTK) and having to balance them with the mundane work I do 9 - 5 on
weekdays has been like missing a WT20 finals because you need to water the
plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, that's the situation as of now. The only driving force I have is this absurd
belief that, since I've finished everything I've &lt;em&gt;'passed'&lt;/em&gt; everything I've
started before, it'll be the same this time around as well. Let's hope lightning
does strike the same place repeatedly.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="uni"></category><category term="oasis"></category><category term="work"></category><category term="casey neistat"></category></entry><entry><title>July</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/july/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-12T23:57:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-12:2016/07/july/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's July, I'm on a twelve week break from &lt;em&gt;jeewanopaya&lt;/em&gt;, it's 
almost midnight and I'm slacking off from doing actual productive
work by checking out static site generators. Pelican seems nice, 
and I've always wanted a hacky, markdown-powered thing for my 
github.io page.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>