<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Janith's Blog</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://janithl.github.io/feeds/links.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://janithl.github.io/</id><updated>2016-08-14T17:53:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Links: August 14</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/links-august-14/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-14T17:53:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-14:2016/08/links-august-14/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/money/2014/10/21/357629765/when-women-stopped-coding"&gt;promised previously&lt;/a&gt; to use this space for link sharing as well, so here
goes the first instalment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On Software&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gender disparity in computer science is an often discussed topic, and the 
following is one of my favourite graphs on the topic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/money/2014/10/21/357629765/when-women-stopped-coding"&gt;&lt;img alt="Women in CompSci" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/comp-sci-women.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I read about another study that confirms that software development 
is not the meritocracy it is often claimed to be. - &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2016/feb/12/women-considered-better-coders-hide-gender-github"&gt;"Women considered better 
coders – but only if they hide their gender"&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The researchers looked at approximately 3m pull requests submitted on GitHub, 
and found that code written by women was approved at a higher rate (78.6%) than 
code written by men (74.6%).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking for an explanation for this disparity, the researchers examined 
several different factors, such as whether women were making smaller changes 
to code (they were not) or whether women were outperforming men in only certain 
kinds of code (they were not). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was here that they made the disturbing discovery: women’s work was more 
likely to be accepted than men’s, unless “their gender is identifiable”, in 
which case the acceptance rate was worse than men’s. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the golden&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jenny Bryan, a professor of statistics at the University of British Columbia, 
uses GitHub as a teacher and developer in R, a programming language. Her profile 
makes clear that she is a woman, and she doesn’t believe that she’s been 
discriminated against due to her gender.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At the very most, men who don’t know me sometimes explain things to me that 
I likely understand better than they do,” she writes. “The men I interact with 
in the R community on GitHub know me and, if my genderhas any effect at all, I 
feel they go out of their way to support my efforts to learn and make more 
contributions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trust Githubbers to attempt mansplaining R to a Stats Prof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Machine Learning is a topic &lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/the-lastfm-dataset/"&gt;I am ostensibly interested in&lt;/a&gt;. This week, I
discovered a really cool &lt;a href="https://github.com/josephmisiti/awesome-machine-learning"&gt;awesome-style list with a ton of ML resources&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awesome Machine Learning Awesome: A curated list of awesome machine learning 
frameworks, libraries and software (by language).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A beautiful, beautiful tool and write-up by &lt;a href="http://www.martinoleary.com/"&gt;Dr. Martin O'Leary of Swansea 
University&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="http://mewo2.com/notes/terrain/"&gt;how to generate imaginary maps&lt;/a&gt; and a companion piece on 
&lt;a href="http://mewo2.com/notes/naming-language/"&gt;generating an imginary language to produce place names&lt;/a&gt;. Mind-blown twice: 
as a cartography nerd AND as someone who studied NLP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Imaginary Maps" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/imaginary-maps.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to make maps that look like something you'd find at the back of one 
of the cheap paperback fantasy novels of my youth. I always had a fascination 
with these imagined worlds, which were often much more interesting than 
whatever luke-warm sub-Tolkien tale they were attached to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Took me back to my childhood spent looking for, devouring and creating 
imaginary maps of my own. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On Sports&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2016/08/08/sports/olympics/history-olympic-dominance-charts.html?_r=0"&gt;beautifully visual and data-rich NYT piece&lt;/a&gt; on how different countries
dominated different arenas of the Olympics over the years, and how certain 
blocks dominate certain sports. Part of their excellent Olympic coverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.espncricinfo.com/sri-lanka-v-australia-2016/content/story/1045673.html"&gt;Andrew Fernando's excellent write-up&lt;/a&gt; on the first day of the third test
between Australia and Sri Lanka at the SSC. He keeps churning out these 
exceptional gems that make me proud to be Sri Lankan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SSC ground happens to be in the clotted heart of Colombo's administrative 
district. Yet, although the Australia team may never set foot inside the 
National Identity Card Centre, which is a few minutes away, or the Ministry of 
Public Administration and Management, which is visible from the ground, they 
were on day one of this Test, given a thorough government-office treatment. 
They were made to wait for hours, run around, given brief hope, which was 
promptly crushed; they were sneered at, and mistreated, and by the end of the 
day, they were ready to tear their hair out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bureaucrat-in-chief for Sri Lanka was Dhananjaya de Silva, whose maiden Test 
hundred was a thing of superlative casualness. So unfazed was he by a scoreline 
of 26 for 5 at his arrival, he was like the civil servant who comes to work to 
find a queue stretching around the building outside his office, yet before work 
takes a long tea-and-biscuit break while chit-chatting to colleagues. He stood 
slouched at the crease all day, unfurling somnolent drives, and languid flicks 
to the leg side, appearing as if he was doing almost nothing. Meanwhile, 
Australia chased leather all over; patrons shunted from room to room to room 
in the building, all, in the end, for no tangible reward. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;swoons&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On Conflict&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Col. Sylvester Perera's &lt;a href="https://globalecco.org/the-sri-lankan-civil-war-a-personal-reminiscence-col-sylvester-perera-sri-lankan-army"&gt;sobering account of the civil war in the 90s&lt;/a&gt;, and 
how lasting peace is yet to be achieved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Operation Riviresa was one of the major operations conducted by Sri Lanka's 
armed forces against the LTTE, and it was both well-planned and 
well-coordinated. The primary objective of the operation was the capture and 
liberation of the town of Jaffna and the rest of the Jaffna peninsula. 
By contrast, during Operation Sath Jaya to capture the LTTE stronghold of 
Kilinochchi, the country's political leadership overrode the advice of military 
commanders and drove the army to stretch its forces beyond the practical limits 
of defense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...] the intelligence provided to the military lacked answers to the vital 
questions of when, where, what, and how—the most fundamental aspects of a 
useful intelligence picture. As a result, our operations either were ineffective 
or became nightmares of shock and surprise for our troops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized that defeating an insurgency does not bring the conflict to a 
conclusive end. I had to put all my efforts into managing a post-conflict 
society for peace building, within a framework called disarmament, 
demobilization, and reintegration. Despite all our work, however, it seems 
that Sri Lanka is still facing these challenges [...]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D. B. S. Jeyaraj's article &lt;a href="http://dbsjeyaraj.com/dbsj/archives/47692"&gt;"Shelton Ranaraja: Principled Politician was 
Conscience-Keeper of the Nation"&lt;/a&gt; which contained some chilling excerpts 
from William Mcgowan's “Only man is Vile”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kandyan jungle seemed so at peace just after dawn on that October morning 
in 1989. In the twisted thicket of palms, bamboo and bougainvillea that 
blanketed the hotel, a handful of iridescent parrots screeched cheery greetings 
to the first rays of sun as they splintered into a forest of prisms through the 
morning dew [...] But we turned left that morning, and we hadn’t driven even a 
mile when we saw our first body–a headless corpse, hands bound behind its back, 
blocking the road like a fallen tree. A few hundred yards farther, there were 
three more, then two more, then four more, all with their heads neatly severed 
at the shoulders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Ranaraja expressed what I imagine a lot of people must've felt at that time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That night, in his modest home near the Temple of the Sacred Relic in downtown 
Kandy, one of the island’s parliamentarians spoke with quiet frustration of the 
trauma that this awful era has caused his island paradise and its 14 million 
people–“We wake up in the morning, and we know tomorrow will be worse than 
today”–and he tried to square the living death with the religion that had taught 
them from birth the sacredness of all life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re not to kill even an animal or an ant,” Shelton Ranaraja said that 
evening, his body shaken and broken from the horrors that abounded in the 
peaceful jungle around him. “I don’t understand why this is happening. I cannot 
explain it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So very glad I got to skip the 80s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, that was a long write (and read, sorry!). I should try to keep these shorter
from next time on.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="conflict"></category><category term="code"></category><category term="data"></category></entry></feed>