<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Janith's Blog - Links</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://janithl.github.io/feeds/links.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://janithl.github.io/</id><updated>2020-02-07T21:50:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Links: January Tunes</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2020/02/links-january-tunes/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-02-07T21:50:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-02-07T21:50:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2020-02-07:/2020/02/links-january-tunes/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;2020 has been an interesting year musically, so here are some of my
favourite music this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Theo Katzman&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4xsfOuLM2J8"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vulf wunderkind Theo's album, "Modern Johnny Sings: Songs in the Age
of Vibe", has been the talk of the town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Cory Wong&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of Vulf alum, Cory's album "Elevator Music for …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;2020 has been an interesting year musically, so here are some of my
favourite music this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Theo Katzman&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4xsfOuLM2J8"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vulf wunderkind Theo's album, "Modern Johnny Sings: Songs in the Age
of Vibe", has been the talk of the town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Cory Wong&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of Vulf alum, Cory's album "Elevator Music for an Elevated Mood"
is also the talk of the town, with bangers such as &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jJXy21fphYo"&gt;"Team Sports"&lt;/a&gt;.
There's also this crazy collab with Dave Koz&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_mCJBzcyHEk"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cory comments on the video:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Dave, can u sit in a directors chair for this one?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"What?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Yea they've got a directors chair...can u sit in it"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Wait, what song?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Read this chart, you'll know exactly what to do...i'll take the solo"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Why aren't you wearing shoes"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Alright we got the 2200 grit sandpaper out, Koz is in the building..."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TAKE 1 RELEASED ON ALBUM&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It blows my mind how good these session regulars/legends are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ryan Lerman/Scary Pockets/Stories/Pomplamoose&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ryan has been putting out a ton of music both from the Scary Pockets
channel as well as the new Stories series. There's this amazing Bieber
cover featuring Antwaun Stanley:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dATGquiB05g"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cool as fuck 'Kill Bill' inspired collaboration with Larry Goldings
(featuring Sam Wilkes on the Fender Whistle):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4yg_XjYju_s"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plenty of cool featured artists on Stories including
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Idrdp_3LctM"&gt;Arlissa covering John Mayer&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=D5Hbcf_2Rac"&gt;Nataly Dawn covering MGMT&lt;/a&gt;. Nataly
has also been recording an album of French language covers, including the
following iconic tune:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/7B4CLQGxHmI"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Reina Del Cid/Josh Turner&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reina did an amazing collab with British singer-songwriter Mary Spender:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/sj2gSmZqjSU"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Josh collaborated with his SO Kelly Oden, for the cutest video of the new year:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UC0wv3p05Wc"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just aww! :')&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;And, finally&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This doesn't count as a 'tune', but it would be criminal to leave this off
the list—Paul Davids and Samurai "Sammy G" Guitarist collab to blow our minds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Uvjf0uUGsVg"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of Sri Lankans would know him from "Dave Koz Radio Show" fame.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="music"></category></entry><entry><title>Links: May 25</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2017/05/links-may-25/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-25T07:33:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-05-25T07:33:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2017-05-25:/2017/05/links-may-25/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Media coverage of ISIS tends to veer from the utilitarian (covering attacks and the daily
body-counts of ongoing operations against them) to the absurd, like the story of &lt;a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation-now/2017/05/02/fbi-translator-secretly-married-islamic-state-leader/309137001/"&gt;how a
"smart but naive" FBI translator fell in love with a German rapper turned ISIS leader&lt;/a&gt;
she was supposed to be …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Media coverage of ISIS tends to veer from the utilitarian (covering attacks and the daily
body-counts of ongoing operations against them) to the absurd, like the story of &lt;a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation-now/2017/05/02/fbi-translator-secretly-married-islamic-state-leader/309137001/"&gt;how a
"smart but naive" FBI translator fell in love with a German rapper turned ISIS leader&lt;/a&gt;
she was supposed to be investigating, and flew over to Syria to marry him &lt;em&gt;(wtaf?!)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately, with Mosul being liberated, sobering reports have come to light of life under 
ISIS, and the violent campaign that freed Mosul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month, &lt;a href="https://scroll.in/article/836791/why-use-rockets-a-blow-by-blow-account-of-how-airstrikes-wrecked-homes-in-mosul-iraq"&gt;Scroll.in&lt;/a&gt; carried the story of two families and their
experiences in the carnage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Khalil then heard a loud whoosh - the sound of incoming rockets. "I recognised it," he
said, having enlisted in the army for the mandatory one-year service after he completed 
college in 2000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first two rockets hit his uncle's house. The impact pushed Khalil into the 
basement. A third rocket landed on his friend's garage. A fourth hit a corner of his own 
house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Everything went dark," he said. "All this happened in 15 minutes."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The "Uncle" in the story is the world-renowned Civil Engineer &lt;a href="http://www.workers.org/2017/01/26/the-battle-for-mosul/#.WQyTvlOGPVo"&gt;Dr Mohamad Tyeb Al-Layla&lt;/a&gt;, who died in the conflict. Generally, education seems to have taken the 
biggest hit during the period of ISIS control. &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-middle-east-39525749"&gt;A BBC report from two days ago&lt;/a&gt; says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our lives under IS were empty and boring as we were locked in our homes. They shut down
our universities and wrote on the front door: "A woman's kingdom is her home". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On universities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of those institutions were shut down, and education under IS was focused on
teaching jihad and combat techniques. Women and men were separated and women were told to
completely cover up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This obsession with female dress was referred to in the earlier story as well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Hafidh's daughter, 21-year-old Nawal] brought out the dress she had to wear under
ISIS: the abaya, or loose-fitting gown, gloves, socks, niqab, or face veil with slits for
the eyes, and an eye-shield on top of it. "We could hardly see when we went out," she
said. Any deviation was punished with fines, whiplashes and street executions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Women in Mosul" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/mosul.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The BBC article carries a more gruesome depiction of what the Hisba (religious police) was
capable of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will never forget that awful day and what happened to a little seven-year-old on our
street. The girl had come down to the small neighbourhood shop to buy some sweets when IS
militants approached her. The girl, chatting innocently to the old shop owner, was asked
by the militants where her home was. She pointed it out before running and hiding. Her
parents come to see what was going on and the IS fighters lectured them about how their
daughter was violating Sharia law by being alone with the seller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a long debate, the fighters decided the girl's punishment was to be bitten or 
pinched in her face or on her hands by the women of the Hisba [the religious police], or 
the more adequately described "monsters of Hisba".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The terrified mother begged them to punish her instead of her young daughter but there
is no room for discussion with IS. The child was punished in front of her screaming
mother. The monsters aggressively and repeatedly beat her and pinched her. The child was
screaming until she passed out and her heart stopped. The wailing mother completely lost
her mind when she saw her child die in front of her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A conflict that has lasted more than half a decade (and has involved everything from
alleged chemical attacks, to drowning toddlers seeking refuge, to young Yazidi girls
forced into sexual slavery) still manages to produce stories of the most senseless crimes
imaginable.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="conflict"></category><category term="geopolitics"></category><category term="religion"></category></entry><entry><title>Links: March 06</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2017/03/links-march-06/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-03-06T21:06:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-03-06T21:06:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2017-03-06:/2017/03/links-march-06/</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Patrio&lt;/s&gt; Posts about links are the last refuge of a scoundrel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we get underway, a status update:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of lines of code I've written in the last 26 days (since I stopped going to
work) is 0, not counting some late night shenanigans where I thought typing some …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Patrio&lt;/s&gt; Posts about links are the last refuge of a scoundrel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we get underway, a status update:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of lines of code I've written in the last 26 days (since I stopped going to
work) is 0, not counting some late night shenanigans where I thought typing some Pandas
code into a terminal was going to solve my issues (it didn't).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, I've devoured BoJack, and started on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Letterkenny_(TV_series)"&gt;Letterkenny&lt;/a&gt;. So, there's 
&lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; progress. Also I finally managed to finish off the first draft of my PGDip report,
typeset it in beautiful LaTeX (&amp;lt;3 &amp;lt;3 &amp;lt;3), and send it in. So hopefully I can get around to 
some real work from now on... &lt;em&gt;*proceeds to write blog post instead*&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/cities/2017/feb/27/sand-mining-global-environmental-crisis-never-heard"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sand mining: the global environmental crisis you've probably never heard of&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tl;dr:&lt;/em&gt; Sand mining sucks, and will destroy ecosystems and infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cities are expanding at a pace and on a scale far greater than at any time in human 
history. The number of people living in urban areas has more than quadrupled since 1950, 
to about 4 billion today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past few years, China has used more cement than the US used in the entire 20th 
century. Last year alone, the nation used enough construction sand to cover the entire 
state of New York an inch deep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*looks wearily over Galle Face at the new port city coming up*&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worldwide, thousands of ships vacuum up millions of tonnes from the seabed each year, 
tearing up habitats and muddying waters with sand plumes that can affect aquatic life far 
from the original site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most dramatic impact of ocean sand mining is surely felt in Indonesia, where sand 
miners have completely erased at least two dozen islands since 2005.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots to learn and think about, especially with our recent issues with both sand mining 
(leading to salinisation of rivers), and the recent controversy (especially in 
&lt;a href="http://www.colombopage.com/archive_17A/Feb12_1486916112CH.php"&gt;Divulapitiya in the Gampaha district&lt;/a&gt;) regarding soil being illegally mined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.wired.com/2017/03/ann-arbor-fighting-traffic-software-winning/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ann Arbor Is Fighting Traffic With Software - and Winning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ann Arbor's adaptive traffic signal control system has been playing god for more than a 
decade, but fiddling engineers continue to tweak its inputs and algorithms. Now it reduces 
weekday travel times on affected corridors by 12 percent, and weekend travel time by 21 
percent. A trip along one busy corridor that took under three minutes just 15 percent of 
the time in 2005 now comes in under that mark 70 percent of the time. That’s enough to 
convince Ann Arbor’s traffic engineers, who just announced they'll extend this system to 
all its downtown traffic lights and its most trafficked corridors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Music to the ears of Colombo commuters stuck in traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, all this may prove little more than a band-aid. Geometry says there are only 
so many ways to fit a bunch of vehicles on to streets. The best way to beat traffic is to 
not be part of traffic at all. It's by moving people onto transit (a regional commuter 
rail plan is hogtied by funding woes and general intransigence), or carpools, or making 
it easier to walk and bicycle. In the meantime, though, computers are pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.vox.com/a/fenn-treasure-hunt-map"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In search of Forrest Fenn's treasure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vox has this wonderful long form piece with video, maps and gorgeous photography. Loved 
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We came here to find a chest filled with $2 million worth of treasure, hidden by an 
eccentric, wealthy 80-year-old man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's poetry with clues, lots of maps and riddles. It's like a Wes Anderson movie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am reminded of a telephone conversation we’d had earlier with Scott King, a treasure 
hunter who failed in his own search. He’d warned us to be wary of &lt;strong&gt;confirmation bias&lt;/strong&gt; - 
interpreting new evidence as validation of one's preexisting beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day, we turn to science. [...] Using geographic data from the clues (e.g., 
between 5,000 and 10,200 feet; near a water source; near pine trees), they'd narrowed down 
the original search area from 27,801,289 acres to 591,636 acres — a 98 percent reduction 
in size. From there, they’d homed in specifically on the Yellowstone National Park area, 
shrinking the search area to a mere 0.084% of the original.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using modern GIS tools for treasure hunting... how abou dah?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this Sunday's Sunday Times (yes, I read the paper whenever I can), two interesting
stories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.sundaytimes.lk/170305/plus/a-tale-of-the-kandyan-royal-architect-and-court-intrigue-231157.html"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A tale of the Kandyan royal architect and court intrigue&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title 'Mulachari' was given to an artificer who was an expert in at least five arts 
and crafts. As John D'Oyly had observed, there were seven artificers under one Mulachari 
and it was a coveted position&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devendra Mulachari is also credited for some of the iconic historic monuments of the 
Kandyan Kingdom including the Pattirippuwa or Octagon of the Dalada Maligawa, Cloud Wall 
(walakulubemma) and the Kandy lake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Lawrie's Gazetteer, Devendra Mulachari's first architectural work was the 
construction of the Bana Maduwa in Middeniya. The place which was used as a meeting place 
for official and unofficial purposes and also as a preaching hall had been demolished 
around 2004 as Mr. Waidyasekera notes and was replaced by a Samurdhi meeting place today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*sigh*&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.sundaytimes.lk/170305/plus/who-are-we-231172.html"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;'Who are we?'&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who are Sri Lankans? From where have we come? Are the major ethnic groups and also the 
Veddahs closely-linked or disparately different? The indisputable findings based on the 
'Eve Gene' or Mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) should lead to stronger bonds among the major 
ethnic groups, making the call 'We are Sri Lankans' louder and clearer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evidence that all Sri Lankan ethnic groups are closely interrelated genetically has 
been piling up for some time, and this is even stronger evidence of that being the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a considerable genetic admixture in contemporary ethnic groups in Sri Lanka - 
the Sinhalese are closely related to the Sri Lankan Tamils. [...] The Muslims and the 
Malays are also closely related to each other. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;West Eurasian haplogroups among the Sinhalese, the Sri Lankan Tamils and the Veddahs 
suggest early migration of women carrying these haplogroups into the country. [...] 
Predominance of Indian mtDNA haplogroups among Muslims and Malays support the notion of 
largely male migration and marriage to local women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study size is not huge (about 200 DNA samples in total), and more sequencing of the 
mtDNA molecule is to be done for even better understanding, but this is pretty sweet. 
Hopefully the findings make a splash among the general public and we can move over the 
bickering and start to move forward as a unified nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two pretty great tools for dataviz, and stats respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the &lt;a href="http://pixelmap.amcharts.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pixel Map Generator&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which lets you paint map segments and draw all 
sorts of symbols on it. Great tool for generating maps, and they have a district map of
Sri Lanka as well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Sri Lanka on Pixel Map Generator" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/pixel-map-sri-lanka.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, &lt;a href="http://students.brown.edu/seeing-theory/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seeing Theory&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a site that uses D3js 
visualisations to explain statistics in an easier to understand way to a wider range of 
students. As someone who's always had trouble with the subject, I'm grateful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's it for now. More, soon. Hopefully more substantive. Or rant-ive. IDK.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="biology"></category><category term="conflict"></category><category term="data"></category><category term="people"></category></entry><entry><title>Links: Machine Learning</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/links-machine-learning/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-25T21:13:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-08-25T21:13:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-25:/2016/08/links-machine-learning/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm changing the format of the links posts to topic-based posts which I will 
add to over time. Seems like a better way to organize than basing them on dates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;August 2016&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://backchannel.com/an-exclusive-look-at-how-ai-and-machine-learning-work-at-apple-8dbfb131932b"&gt;&lt;em&gt;An exclusive inside look at how artificial intelligence and machine learning 
work at Apple&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fascinating look at …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm changing the format of the links posts to topic-based posts which I will 
add to over time. Seems like a better way to organize than basing them on dates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;August 2016&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://backchannel.com/an-exclusive-look-at-how-ai-and-machine-learning-work-at-apple-8dbfb131932b"&gt;&lt;em&gt;An exclusive inside look at how artificial intelligence and machine learning 
work at Apple&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fascinating look at how ML work is being done at Apple, and how it meshes 
with privacy of user data and the "Apple way" of absolute secrecy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple’s penchant for secrecy puts it at a disadvantage against competitors 
who encourage their star computer scientists to widely share research with the 
world. “Our practices tend to reinforce a natural selection bias — those who are 
interested in working as a team to deliver a great product versus those whose 
primary motivation is publishing,” says Federighi. If while improving an Apple 
product scientists happen to make breakthroughs in the field, that’s great. “But 
we are driven by a vision of the end result,” says Cue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://adeshpande3.github.io/adeshpande3.github.io/The-9-Deep-Learning-Papers-You-Need-To-Know-About.html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The 9 Deep Learning Papers You Need To Know About&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great overview of some recent breakthrough research in CNNs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...] a lot of the new and important developments in the field of computer 
vision and convolutional neural networks. [...] The first half of the list 
(AlexNet to ResNet) deals with advancements in general network architecture, 
while the second half is just a collection of interesting papers in other 
subareas. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/@ageitgey/machine-learning-is-fun-part-5-language-translation-with-deep-learning-and-the-magic-of-sequences-2ace0acca0aa"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Language Translation with Deep Learning and the Magic of Sequences&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The magic of sequence-to-sequence learning, taking a crack at the 'holy grail'
of Computational Lingustics: Machine Translation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we took two RNNs and hooked them up end-to-end? The first RNN could 
generate the encoding that represents a sentence. Then the second RNN could take 
that encoding and just do the same logic in reverse to decode the original 
sentence again [...] what if (and here’s the big idea!) we could train the 
second RNN to decode the sentence into Spanish instead of English?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With promising results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Machine learning researchers only invented this two years ago, but it’s 
already performing as well as statistical machine translation systems that took 
20 years to develop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And wider applications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About a year ago, researchers at Google showed that you can use 
sequence-to-sequence models to build AI bots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...] by replacing the first RNN with a Convolutional Neural Network [...] we 
can turn pictures into words (as long as we have lots and lots of training 
data)! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrej Karpathy expanded on these ideas to build a system capable of 
describing images in great detail by processing multiple regions of an image 
separately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://research.googleblog.com/2016/08/text-summarization-with-tensorflow.html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Text summarization with TensorFlow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish Google will stop stealing all our research topics. :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve observed that due to the nature of news headlines, the model can 
generate good headlines from reading just a few sentences from the beginning of 
the article. Although this task serves as a nice proof-of-concept, we started 
looking at more difficult datasets where reading the entire document is 
necessary to produce good summaries. In those tasks training from scratch with 
this model architecture does not do as well as some other techniques we’re 
researching, but it serves as a baseline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels like TensorFlow (and SyntaxNet) is really taking the NLP world by 
storm, especially looking at &lt;a href="https://research.googleblog.com/2016/08/acl-2016-research-at-google.html"&gt;Google's offerings at ACL 2016&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://code.facebook.com/posts/561187904071636/segmenting-and-refining-images-with-sharpmask/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Segmenting and refining images with SharpMask&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not wanting to be left out, Facebook has also released some incredible research
in the past few weeks, earlier with &lt;a href="https://research.facebook.com/blog/fasttext/"&gt;fastText&lt;/a&gt; and now extending to DeepMask 
and SharpMask:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DeepMask employs a fairly traditional feedforward deep network design. In such 
networks, with progressively deeper network stages information is more abstract 
and semantically meaningful. For example, early layers in a deep net might 
capture edges and blobs, while upper layers tend to capture more semantic 
concepts such as the presence of an animal's face or limbs. By design, these 
upper-layer features are computed at a fairly low spatial resolution (for both 
computational reasons and in order to be invariant to small shifts in pixel 
locations). This presents a problem for mask prediction: The upper layer 
features can be used to predict masks that capture the general shape on an 
object but fail to precisely capture object boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings us to SharpMask. SharpMask refines the output of DeepMask, 
generating higher-fidelity masks that more accurately delineate object 
boundaries. While DeepMask predicts coarse masks in a feedforward pass through 
the network, SharpMask reverses the flow of information in a deep network and 
refines the predictions made by DeepMask by using features from progressively 
earlier layers in the network. Think of it this way: To capture general object 
shape, you have to have a high-level understanding of what you are looking at 
(DeepMask), but to accurately place the boundaries you need to look back at 
lower-level features all the way down to the pixels (SharpMask). In essence, we 
aim to make use of information from all layers of a network, with minimal 
additional overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They've also done some work on real time (video) classification:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, our next challenge will be to apply these techniques to video, 
where objects are moving, interacting, and changing over time. We've already 
made some progress with computer vision techniques to watch videos and 
understand and classify what's in them in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="code"></category><category term="data"></category><category term="machine learning"></category></entry><entry><title>Pairplots FTW! Links: August 15</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/links-august-15/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-15T20:06:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-08-15T20:06:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-15:/2016/08/links-august-15/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Instalment 2 of the "sharing links" thingy. Shorter too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Software:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently subscribed to the Dataquest newsletter, and today got this post
emailed to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.dataquest.io/blog/python-vs-r/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Python vs R: head to head data analysis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make pairwise scatterplots: One common way to explore a dataset is to see how 
different columns …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Instalment 2 of the "sharing links" thingy. Shorter too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Software:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently subscribed to the Dataquest newsletter, and today got this post
emailed to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.dataquest.io/blog/python-vs-r/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Python vs R: head to head data analysis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make pairwise scatterplots: One common way to explore a dataset is to see how 
different columns correlate to others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Seaborn Pairplot" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/seaborn-pairplot.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above example is from the excellent &lt;a href="https://stanford.edu/~mwaskom/software/seaborn/generated/seaborn.pairplot.html"&gt;Seaborn Documentation&lt;/a&gt;. Good stuff!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Conflict:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read several great D. B. S. Jeyaraj articles in my ongoing fascination with
the Sri Lankan Civil War.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://dbsjeyaraj.com/dbsj/archives/1073"&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Pottu Amman” and the Intelligence Division of the LTTE&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was amazed at Pottu’s growth in later life and observed “I just don’t know 
how he is running the intelligence division so well nowadays”. But then academic 
brilliance is not a pre-requisite to run an intelligence outfit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is required is lateral thinking, practical approaches, devious cunning, 
organizational skills, shrewd judgement of men and matters and above all 
perpetual paranoia about everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://dbsjeyaraj.com/dbsj/archives/14588"&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Col Charles”: The ”tiger” Mastermind Behind LTTE Attacks Outside 
North-East&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was decided that Colombo should be taught a bitter lesson. Charles, then 
only nineteen was entrusted with the task. He moved into Colombo in January 1991 
and set two plans of attack in motion. Within a few weeks the LTTE struck in 
Colombo. The JOC headquarters was blown up. Ranjan Wijeratne was killed by a car 
bomb. This was only the beginning. Charles as an “unknown face” of the LTTE 
remained incognito in Colombo till 1997.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How inept was military intel at that time for this guy to lurk around for almost
7 years blowing shit up and not be noticed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Economics:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The excellent piece on the Daily FT by IPS Chairman Prof. Razeen Sally, titled 
&lt;a href="http://www.ft.lk/article/560914/ft"&gt;&lt;em&gt;"The Sri Lankan economy after regime change"&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First the Government hammers consumers with high prices through inflation and 
import taxes – which hits the poor particularly hard since they spend more of 
their disposable income on essential items. Then it bludgeons producers with 
price controls. This is market-busting, an echo of Mrs Bandaranaike’s command 
economy in the 1970s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the same old wine in new bottles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Old, established politicians have played musical chairs around the cabinet 
table, and kept a new generation of younger, competent professionals away from 
positions of power. This is not surprising: the old political elite – and their 
business cronies – have vested interests to defend. And so entrenched, 
unprofessional, bankrupt attitudes and methods persist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On tax reform:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objectives should be to get revenue up to 15-20% of GDP, while concurrently 
increasing incentives to save, invest, create jobs and boost productivity. The 
watchword should be “simplification”. There should be clean, simple rates for 
VAT and direct (personal and corporate) income taxes, with as few exemptions as 
possible. [...] Even relatively low tax rates will generate more revenue 
providing the system is clean, simple and well-enforced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the possible repercussions of this government failing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more malign scenario is that the present situation will spiral backwards. 
A macroeconomic crisis might be the catalyst. Or it could result from popular 
frustrations – no new investments, no new jobs, no change – boiling over. Then, 
in the Sinhala-Buddhist heartland, people might yearn again for a Big Man, a 
Rajapaksa or someone else, to ride in and clean house, sweeping away liberal 
rights and democratic niceties with his authoritarian broom. They could vent 
their frustrations at the minorities who got President Sirisena and a UNP-led 
Government elected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hat tip for &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/yudhanjaya"&gt;Yudhanjaya&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/himalkk"&gt;Himal&lt;/a&gt; for pointing me at this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been watching a LOT of "Crash Course World History", and I loved their 
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=alJaltUmrGo"&gt;&lt;em&gt;episode on Imperialism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, especially the oft-overlooked economic side of 
it. See also &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QfsfoFqsFk4"&gt;their episode on American Imperialism&lt;/a&gt;, mostly covering the 
Spanish-American War.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/alJaltUmrGo" 
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I guess not that much shorter. Oh well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="conflict"></category><category term="data"></category><category term="geopolitics"></category></entry><entry><title>Links: August 14</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/links-august-14/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-14T17:53:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-08-14T17:53:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-14:/2016/08/links-august-14/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/money/2014/10/21/357629765/when-women-stopped-coding"&gt;promised previously&lt;/a&gt; to use this space for link sharing as well, so here
goes the first instalment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Software:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gender disparity in computer science is an often discussed topic, and the 
following is one of my favourite graphs on the topic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/money/2014/10/21/357629765/when-women-stopped-coding"&gt;&lt;img alt="Women in CompSci" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/comp-sci-women.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I read about another study that …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/money/2014/10/21/357629765/when-women-stopped-coding"&gt;promised previously&lt;/a&gt; to use this space for link sharing as well, so here
goes the first instalment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Software:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gender disparity in computer science is an often discussed topic, and the 
following is one of my favourite graphs on the topic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/money/2014/10/21/357629765/when-women-stopped-coding"&gt;&lt;img alt="Women in CompSci" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/comp-sci-women.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I read about another study that confirms that software development 
is not the meritocracy it is often claimed to be. - &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2016/feb/12/women-considered-better-coders-hide-gender-github"&gt;"Women considered better 
coders – but only if they hide their gender"&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The researchers looked at approximately 3m pull requests submitted on GitHub, 
and found that code written by women was approved at a higher rate (78.6%) than 
code written by men (74.6%).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking for an explanation for this disparity, the researchers examined 
several different factors, such as whether women were making smaller changes 
to code (they were not) or whether women were outperforming men in only certain 
kinds of code (they were not). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was here that they made the disturbing discovery: women’s work was more 
likely to be accepted than men’s, unless “their gender is identifiable”, in 
which case the acceptance rate was worse than men’s. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the golden&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jenny Bryan, a professor of statistics at the University of British Columbia, 
uses GitHub as a teacher and developer in R, a programming language. Her profile 
makes clear that she is a woman, and she doesn’t believe that she’s been 
discriminated against due to her gender.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At the very most, men who don’t know me sometimes explain things to me that 
I likely understand better than they do,” she writes. “The men I interact with 
in the R community on GitHub know me and, if my genderhas any effect at all, I 
feel they go out of their way to support my efforts to learn and make more 
contributions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trust Githubbers to attempt mansplaining R to a Stats Prof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Machine Learning is a topic &lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/the-lastfm-dataset/"&gt;I am ostensibly interested in&lt;/a&gt;. This week, I
discovered a really cool &lt;a href="https://github.com/josephmisiti/awesome-machine-learning"&gt;awesome-style list with a ton of ML resources&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awesome Machine Learning Awesome: A curated list of awesome machine learning 
frameworks, libraries and software (by language).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A beautiful, beautiful tool and write-up by &lt;a href="http://www.martinoleary.com/"&gt;Dr. Martin O'Leary of Swansea 
University&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="http://mewo2.com/notes/terrain/"&gt;how to generate imaginary maps&lt;/a&gt; and a companion piece on 
&lt;a href="http://mewo2.com/notes/naming-language/"&gt;generating an imginary language to produce place names&lt;/a&gt;. Mind-blown twice: 
as a cartography nerd AND as someone who studied NLP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Imaginary Maps" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/imaginary-maps.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to make maps that look like something you'd find at the back of one 
of the cheap paperback fantasy novels of my youth. I always had a fascination 
with these imagined worlds, which were often much more interesting than 
whatever luke-warm sub-Tolkien tale they were attached to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Took me back to my childhood spent looking for, devouring and creating 
imaginary maps of my own. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Sports:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2016/08/08/sports/olympics/history-olympic-dominance-charts.html?_r=0"&gt;beautifully visual and data-rich NYT piece&lt;/a&gt; on how different countries
dominated different arenas of the Olympics over the years, and how certain 
blocks dominate certain sports. Part of their excellent Olympic coverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.espncricinfo.com/sri-lanka-v-australia-2016/content/story/1045673.html"&gt;Andrew Fernando's excellent write-up&lt;/a&gt; on the first day of the third test
between Australia and Sri Lanka at the SSC. He keeps churning out these 
exceptional gems that make me proud to be Sri Lankan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SSC ground happens to be in the clotted heart of Colombo's administrative 
district. Yet, although the Australia team may never set foot inside the 
National Identity Card Centre, which is a few minutes away, or the Ministry of 
Public Administration and Management, which is visible from the ground, they 
were on day one of this Test, given a thorough government-office treatment. 
They were made to wait for hours, run around, given brief hope, which was 
promptly crushed; they were sneered at, and mistreated, and by the end of the 
day, they were ready to tear their hair out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bureaucrat-in-chief for Sri Lanka was Dhananjaya de Silva, whose maiden Test 
hundred was a thing of superlative casualness. So unfazed was he by a scoreline 
of 26 for 5 at his arrival, he was like the civil servant who comes to work to 
find a queue stretching around the building outside his office, yet before work 
takes a long tea-and-biscuit break while chit-chatting to colleagues. He stood 
slouched at the crease all day, unfurling somnolent drives, and languid flicks 
to the leg side, appearing as if he was doing almost nothing. Meanwhile, 
Australia chased leather all over; patrons shunted from room to room to room 
in the building, all, in the end, for no tangible reward. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;swoons&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Conflict:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Col. Sylvester Perera's &lt;a href="https://globalecco.org/the-sri-lankan-civil-war-a-personal-reminiscence-col-sylvester-perera-sri-lankan-army"&gt;sobering account of the civil war in the 90s&lt;/a&gt;, and 
how lasting peace is yet to be achieved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Operation Riviresa was one of the major operations conducted by Sri Lanka's 
armed forces against the LTTE, and it was both well-planned and 
well-coordinated. The primary objective of the operation was the capture and 
liberation of the town of Jaffna and the rest of the Jaffna peninsula. 
By contrast, during Operation Sath Jaya to capture the LTTE stronghold of 
Kilinochchi, the country's political leadership overrode the advice of military 
commanders and drove the army to stretch its forces beyond the practical limits 
of defense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...] the intelligence provided to the military lacked answers to the vital 
questions of when, where, what, and how—the most fundamental aspects of a 
useful intelligence picture. As a result, our operations either were ineffective 
or became nightmares of shock and surprise for our troops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized that defeating an insurgency does not bring the conflict to a 
conclusive end. I had to put all my efforts into managing a post-conflict 
society for peace building, within a framework called disarmament, 
demobilization, and reintegration. Despite all our work, however, it seems 
that Sri Lanka is still facing these challenges [...]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D. B. S. Jeyaraj's article &lt;a href="http://dbsjeyaraj.com/dbsj/archives/47692"&gt;"Shelton Ranaraja: Principled Politician was 
Conscience-Keeper of the Nation"&lt;/a&gt; which contained some chilling excerpts 
from William Mcgowan's “Only man is Vile”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kandyan jungle seemed so at peace just after dawn on that October morning 
in 1989. In the twisted thicket of palms, bamboo and bougainvillea that 
blanketed the hotel, a handful of iridescent parrots screeched cheery greetings 
to the first rays of sun as they splintered into a forest of prisms through the 
morning dew [...] But we turned left that morning, and we hadn’t driven even a 
mile when we saw our first body–a headless corpse, hands bound behind its back, 
blocking the road like a fallen tree. A few hundred yards farther, there were 
three more, then two more, then four more, all with their heads neatly severed 
at the shoulders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Ranaraja expressed what I imagine a lot of people must've felt at that time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That night, in his modest home near the Temple of the Sacred Relic in downtown 
Kandy, one of the island’s parliamentarians spoke with quiet frustration of the 
trauma that this awful era has caused his island paradise and its 14 million 
people–“We wake up in the morning, and we know tomorrow will be worse than 
today”–and he tried to square the living death with the religion that had taught 
them from birth the sacredness of all life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re not to kill even an animal or an ant,” Shelton Ranaraja said that 
evening, his body shaken and broken from the horrors that abounded in the 
peaceful jungle around him. “I don’t understand why this is happening. I cannot 
explain it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So very glad I got to skip the 80s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, that was a long write (and read, sorry!). I should try to keep these shorter
from next time on.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="conflict"></category><category term="code"></category><category term="data"></category></entry></feed>