<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Janith's Blog</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://janithl.github.io/feeds/personal.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://janithl.github.io/</id><updated>2016-12-31T21:24:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>One Last 2016 Post</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/12/one-last-2016-post/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-31T21:24:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-12-31:2016/12/one-last-2016-post/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;2016 has been... an &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; year. I've made friends, and I've lost some.
I got a lot of time to sit down and reflect, and I grow thankful every day for
the people who choose to stand by me despite all my shortcomings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of 2016, let me turn the things that made me happy this year into
a Top 5 list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;1. I got to travel&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since "the incident" of Feb 2014, I've not really travelled as much as I
would've normally liked to. This year though began with some travel: to
Pasikuda with the family. Places I got to travel to this year includes that
and our usual annual trips to Kandy, Anuradhapura (and Yapahuwa, a first for 
me), &lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/09/somawathiya-september-2016/"&gt;Somawathiya&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;Deep South&lt;/em&gt; (Katharagama, Mulkirigala etc.) and 
some really fun day trips Down South with the co-workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Deep South Instagrams" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/deep-south.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was particularly happy with the pics I got to take on the Deep South trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;2. I got to learn&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... both in and out of the classroom. In the classroom I tried to wrap my head
around ML techniques, &lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/and-so-it-began/"&gt;neural nets&lt;/a&gt;, advanced DBs and their ilk. Outside
of it, I got to play with React quite a bit, learn &lt;a href="https://laravel.com/"&gt;Laravel&lt;/a&gt; in a (cramped)
couple of months and push out live systems almost immediately (what a beautiful
framework, has changed the way I write PHP for the better). I got to dabble in
more Python than I ever got to. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got into &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCzZCiVjRPPDCpP5l7HIGRtA"&gt;some&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC3Wj9aO8VS5ZuXrtWfJf81w"&gt;crazy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCCOIcdii1bQmfSPHeNNw4Qw"&gt;YouTube channels&lt;/a&gt; that inspired me to pick 
up my guitar after years, adjust the truss rod and play some barre chords. I
followed Casey Neistat as he built and sold a company, and let John Green
teach me history like I was taking my AP exams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;3. I got time off&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got three months off to write my thesis' lit review, write this blog, &lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/09/the-unp-at-70/"&gt;write 
about the UNP&lt;/a&gt; and write code to buff up my Github profile. I started working
at YAMU the week after I was done with my final exam at uni, and I never got a 
proper break since. Those 3 months let me put everything in perspective and 
helped me decide what I really wanted to do with my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;4. I got bald&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, started balding. Not really fussed about it. (I feel that) I am well aware 
of my mortality, and that I'm no longer the youngest guy in the room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;5. I got to let go&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... of some important things which I once thought would stay with me for (most
of my) life. It was much easier than I thought and I feel much better for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is a stream and hanging on to a bank is not going to help when eventually
we all need to float away. Or so I feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Facebook Year in Review" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/fb-2016.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, that's been my year. It wasn't terrible personally by a long stretch, but
it was certainly challenging and 2017 promises to be even more so. I hope you've
all had a good year, and wish you all the best for the next one. Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>...</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/12/ellipsis/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-15T05:06:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-12-15:2016/12/ellipsis/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;විපතෙහි සැපතෙහි&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;නොසැළෙයි නොතැවෙයි&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;අටලෝ දම හුරු හෙළයා&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="people"></category><category term="sinhala"></category></entry><entry><title>දෙසැම්බර්</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/12/december/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-04T21:46:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-12-04:2016/12/december/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;ලියන්නද දේවල් නැත්තෙ, ලියන්න වචනනම් ගලන්නෙ හැබැයි ඉඩෝරෙට වතුර කැපුවාම 
කරාමෙන් එන වතුර බින්දු වගේ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ගියමාසෙ මම ලිව්වෙ design හුට පටයක් ගැන. එව්වනම් මොනාහරි කොරල ගොඩදාගන්න 
බැරියැ. 'ඒ සිඟිති ප්‍රශ්න ආයෙ දීපන්' කියල හිතෙනව මේ දවස් වල සීන් දැක්කහම.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;තමන් බොහොම අමාරුවෙන්, අවුරුදු ගානක් කැප කරල හදාගත්ත වටිනා බෙහෙත් ගහක් අවිදිමත් 
ඉදිකිරීමක් කරද්දි උගුල්ලලා දැම්මොත් දැනෙන්නෙ කොහොම වේදනාවක්ද? දුකක්ද? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;අර ගියපාර කිව්ව වගේ කිසිදෙයක් 'මමය මාගේය' කියල අල්ලගත්තොත් හැමදාටම ලෝකෙත් 
එක්ක ඕව ගැන කෙලගැනිලි.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ඉතිං අතෑරපං. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;නැත්තං &lt;em&gt;'දුක යනු...'&lt;/em&gt; කියල මීම් හද හද ඉන්න තමයි වෙන්නෙ. :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="මහනුවර වැල් බෝධිය" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/vel-bodhiya.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="work"></category><category term="sinhala"></category></entry><entry><title>November</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/11/november/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-07T07:35:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-11-07:2016/11/november/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;With any sufficiently complex system, a major overhaul always creates 
more problems than it solves; there's enough and more "case studies" of
the type you read about in &lt;em&gt;Software Engineering&lt;/em&gt; to back it up. Things 
that were fixed over years and countless late night hacking sessions and 
painstaking iterations break and you have to fix them again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wisest programmer I've ever met once said that software development 
at scale is all about &lt;em&gt;"letting go"&lt;/em&gt;. I won't say I'm anywhere near 
that level of Zen, but I'm certainly much less OCD about the giant fire 
in the room. It's a pointless to make reversing entropy your life's work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="This Is Fine" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/this-is-fine.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="work"></category></entry><entry><title>Listen To The Girl</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/10/listen-to-the-girl/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-27T20:40:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-10-27:2016/10/listen-to-the-girl/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So much going on right now, and all I want to do is run away and get a 
good night's sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5WKZ26Y_h7A" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</summary><category term="music"></category><category term="people"></category></entry><entry><title>අභය ලිබ්රේ වලට මාරු වීම</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/10/abhaya-libre/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-15T23:30:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-10-15:2016/10/abhaya-libre/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Abhaya Libre" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/abhaya-libre.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;දැං මේ බ්ලොග් එකේ අන්තර්ගතයට (සිංහල හා ලතින් අකුරු සඳහා) සම්පූර්ණයෙන්ම යොදාගන්නෙ 
අභය ලිබ්රේ අකුරු මුහුණතයි. ප්‍රවීන අකුරු මෝස්තර නිර්මාණ ශිල්පී පුෂ්පානන්ද ඒකනායක 
මහතාගේ  &lt;strong&gt;'එෆ් එම් අභය'&lt;/strong&gt; මුහුණතෙන් පරිණාමය වූ මෙය, ඒ මහතාගේ පූර්ණ සහය ඇතිව 
පැතුම් එගොඩවත්ත ප්‍රමුඛ මූනියක් සමූහයෙන් 
&lt;a href="https://github.com/mooniak/abhaya-libre-font"&gt;"සම්පූර්ණ නිදහස්, හිමිකමින් තොර, යුනිකෝඩ් අනුකූලතා පහසුකම සහිත"&lt;/a&gt; අකුරු 
මුහුණතක් විදිහට &lt;a href="https://fonts.google.com/specimen/Abhaya+Libre"&gt;Google Web Fonts නාමාවලියට එක් කරල තියෙනව&lt;/a&gt;. ඔබේ වෙබ් 
පිටුව සඳහාත් මෙය ලබාගන්න පුළුවන්. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Web Fonts පිටුවෙ කියන විදිහටනම් දැනටමත් අඩවි 1,131ක විතර 'අභය ලිබ්රේ' 
භාවිතා වෙනවලු.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;යාවත්කාලීන කිරීම:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;මේක මම ඊයෙ මහ රෑ නිදාගන්න කලින් ලියපු පෝස්ටුවක් නිසා වැදගත් කරුණු ටිකක් කියන්න බැරි
උනා.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;සිංහල වෙබ් අකුරු මුහුණතක් මෙතරම් වැදගත් වෙන්නෙ ඇයි?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Sinhala Not Rendering" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/sinhala-not-rendering.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;සිංහල යුනිකේත වෙබ් අඩවි කියවන අයෙක් නම් ඔයගොල්ලන්ට අනේක වාරයක් මේ වගේ තිර දැකල
පුරුදු ඇති. තමන් පාවිච්චි කරන පරිගණකෙ හරි මෘදුකාංගෙ හරි සිංහල ස්ථාපිත කරල නැතිකොට 
තමයි මේක වෙන්නෙ. සාමන්‍යයෙන් පරිගණකයක (වින්ඩෝස්, ඇපල් හෝ ලිනක්ස්) සිංහල 
අටෝගන්න එතරම් අමාරු නෑ, හැබැයි &lt;a href="http://blog.malinthe.com/2014/04/how-to-get-perfect-sinhala-text-on-android-4-4-kitkat/"&gt;ඇන්ඩ්‍රොයිඩ් වගේ පද්ධතියක "රූට්" කිරිලි වගේ ලොකු
ලොකු සෙල්ලං දාන්න වෙනව&lt;/a&gt; සිංහල දාගන්න. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;වෙබ් අකුරු මුහුණතක තියෙන අපූරුම දේ තමයි තමන්ගෙ යන්තරේට කිසිම දෙයක් අලුතෙන් 
අටවන්නෙ නැතුවම සිංහල පාවිච්චි කරන්න පුලුවන් වෙන එක. ඒ වගේම ඒ ඒ පද්ධතියට ආවේනික
මුහුණතින් පෙන්නන්නෙ නැතුව හැමතැනම (iOS වේවා, වින්ඩෝස් වේවා, ඇන්ඩ්‍රොයිඩ් වේවා) 
එකම් සම්මත අකුරු මුහුණතකින්  තමන්ගෙ වචන ටික දිස් වෙන එක.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Cross Platform" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/abhaya-libre-ios-android.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;මීට කලිනුත් ෆොන්ට් තිබ්බනෙ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ඔව්. &lt;strong&gt;"මලිති වෙබ්"&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;"ඉස්කෝල පොත"&lt;/strong&gt; වගේ ගොඩක් අකුරු මුහුණත් තිබ්බා. ඒත් 
ඒව එකක්වත්  "සම්පූර්ණ නිදහස්, හිමිකමින් තොර, යුනිකෝඩ් අනුකූලතා පහසුකම සහිත" කියන 
කාණ්ඩ තුනටම අයත් වුනේ නෑ. ඒ නිසා නිදහසේ පාවිච්චි කරන්න පුළුවන් web font එකක් සිංහල 
සඳහා තිබ්බෙ නෑ. මේක සිංහල අන්තර්ජාල භාවිතය කෙරෙහි බරපතල ප්‍රශ්නයක් බවට පත්වුනා.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;තව තොරතුරු තියෙනවද?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;මූනියක් සමූහයේ &lt;a href="http://blog.mooniak.com/"&gt;බ්ලොග් අඩවිය&lt;/a&gt; සහ &lt;a href="https://github.com/mooniak/"&gt;ගිට්හබ් පිටුව&lt;/a&gt; කියවල බලන්නකො. ලංකාවෙ
දැනට අකුරු මුහුණත් ක්‍ෂේත්‍රයේ අළුත් දෙයක් කරන නිර්මාණශීලී යොවුන් පිරිසක් විදිහට මොවුන්ව 
හඳුන්වන්න පුළුවන්.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="sinhala"></category><category term="design"></category></entry><entry><title>Octupdate</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/10/octupdate/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-15T11:51:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-10-15:2016/10/octupdate/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, I expected this deluge of werk werk werk to sweep me off my feet, 
but it has been pretty thoroughly overwhelming to get back in the 
saddle. In the last two weeks I have encountered highs and lows that 
staying at home comfortably cushioned me from for weeks, got food 
poisoning, and went back to my role as office plumber-in-chief. My god, 
&lt;strong&gt;so much plumbing&lt;/strong&gt;, and so much more to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Armoured Tuk" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/mal-working.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's so much (loud) activity in the office that Mal and I had to seek 
refuge downstairs to get work done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The traffic has gotten totes ridics now, you can't find a bus with seats 
at 1930 any more. Or hope to get home within the hour. Total &lt;em&gt;ඔබට 
සතුටුයිද දැන්&lt;/em&gt; situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And to top it off I had to go drink a buttermilk and it gave me the 
shits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such is life.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="work"></category><category term="biology"></category></entry><entry><title>Armoured Tuk</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/10/armoured-tuk/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-09T23:06:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-10-09:2016/10/armoured-tuk/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Armoured Tuk" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/armoured-tuk-indexed.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For &lt;a href="https://cerno.wordpress.com/2009/09/25/armoured-trishaw-book-banned/"&gt;Cerno&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="comics"></category><category term="conflict"></category></entry><entry><title>Me IRL</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/09/me-irl/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-27T11:30:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-09-27:2016/09/me-irl/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lightsaber Jan" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/lightsaber-jan.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Done using the usual process. Pencil on paper, inked with an Atlas 
Chooty Gel, and photographed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lightsaber Jan Drawing" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/lightsaber-jan-drawing.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's then cleaned up in GIMP, and traced into a vector in Inkscape, 
resulting in an outline:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lightsaber Jan Outline" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/lightsaber-jan-outline.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then reimported into GIMP, coloured, and highlights and shadows added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've done a Luke and switched from a blue lightsaber to a green one.
I've also forgotten to add the beard, and the legs look atrocious, but
such is life for a nooblet at drawing.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="design"></category><category term="comics"></category></entry><entry><title>3 Fictional Characters...</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/09/3-fictional-characters/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-26T21:37:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-09-26:2016/09/3-fictional-characters/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;...that are somehow supposed to describe your entire being. I saw the tag going
around. No one has tagged me, but when has that ever stopped me?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has proven to be much more difficult than I imagined, not because I don't
have fictional characters that I can relate to, but because...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, see, this is the thing. There are parts of yourself, character traits, 
that you like to think define you. These are all great and noble things, the 
Gryffindor of character traits, all golden and perfect. The naked truth,
though, is that that's what you &lt;em&gt;want to be&lt;/em&gt;, not really who you are in reality. 
When you do, in the sober light of day, do an honest assessment of things, you 
do fall desperately short in quite a few departments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhoo, after days of thinking about this, I finally got my three:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. Harrymort, &lt;a href="https://www.fanfiction.net/s/10677106/1/Seventh-Horcrux"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Seventh Horcrux&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear god, I really wanted to write about how much I &lt;strong&gt;absolutely LOVED&lt;/strong&gt; this 
fanfic. And I &lt;em&gt;despise&lt;/em&gt; fanfics as a rule. But please, guys, do yourselves a 
favour: get off that Pottermore trash and read &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt;. Pliss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Harrymort" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/harrymort.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, Harrymort is brilliant (and described by the author as "a series of bad 
decisions executed well"). He is remorseless and persistent, and did I mention 
brilliant? These are all character traits I tend to fanboy over, being so 
intelligent that even when you mess up, you've done such a good job of it that 
your failures are just as spectacular as when you win. They don't really 
describe me though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Evanesco troll," I murmured. The troll disappeared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hero worship filled my minion's Weasley eyes. "Wicked."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hermione asked, "Where did it go?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I shrugged. "Where does anything that's vanished go?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We stood there for a few minutes, contemplating the nature of nonexistence. At 
least that's what I was doing. I don't know about the children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, shortly after we all should have died horrible deaths via bludgeoning, 
the professors arrived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I do relate to a lot is his constant paranoia, and seeing conspiracies and 
intrigue everywhere (because if you're doing it, everyone else must be too, 
right?). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harrymort is so wrapped up in his lies that he starts to believe them, like his
absolute assertion that Hermione is a dark witch, Ron's a werewolf, and that
Muggle-born wizards and witches have been left behind by their magical parents 
with Muggles acting as childcare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I absolutely adore him. GO READ, NOW.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. Mark Brendanawicz, &lt;em&gt;Parks and Rec&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Parks and Rec" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/parks-and-rec.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Brendanawicz? More like Brendana-Quits!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why a character from the shows difficult beginnings? Why a really bland and 
unlovable character who didn't make an impact from a show full of strong and 
lovable characters?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After years of his life wasted in the city planning (a subject I deeply love) 
department, he finally quit to go work in the private sector. He makes silly 
decisions (Ann), breaks his legs, almost humiliates himself with by proposing 
to a woman who's about to break up with him, and leaves behind the people he
&lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; loved (Leslie). Despite all the crashing and burning, he was perhaps
one of the most realistic characters in a show full of superhumans. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They even threw out his plans for the park and got someone from Eagleton (!!) 
to redraw the thing. Such is life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. Max Fischer, &lt;em&gt;Rushmore&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Max Fischer" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/max-rosemary.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I, just like Max, like to think of myself as a grown-up and an intellectual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I, just like Max, am nothing of the sort. When you finally do meet an actual 
adult (like Rosemary - who Max sees as an &lt;em&gt;equal&lt;/em&gt; and a potential partner), your 
embarrassing childishness shows, you are incapable of processing how to handle 
a real relationship, and your Latin is terrible (or rather, &lt;em&gt;nonexistent&lt;/em&gt;, 
because you foolishly tried to get rid of it from the curriculum).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know, you and Herman deserve each other. You're both little children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we've all been Max at a point in our lives. When we realize that even at 
our best, we're still not &lt;em&gt;good enough&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="people"></category><category term="films"></category><category term="wes anderson"></category></entry><entry><title>Somawathiya, September 2016</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/09/somawathiya-september-2016/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-19T12:16:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-09-19:2016/09/somawathiya-september-2016/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Somawathiya" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/somawathiya.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shot in the early morning light.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="travel"></category></entry><entry><title>When You Say Nothing At All</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/09/when-you-say-nothing-at-all/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-15T06:28:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-09-15:2016/09/when-you-say-nothing-at-all/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Comic" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/wysnaa-comic.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not based on a true story (I hope?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;මෙහි එන සියළු නම් ගම් මනඃකල්පිතය.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="comics"></category><category term="people"></category></entry><entry><title>Sweet Lime?</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/09/sweet-lime/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-04T22:15:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-09-04:2016/09/sweet-lime/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Sweet Lime?" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/sweet-lime.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Sweet Lime?" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/sweet-lime-2.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much love for this film, and for Rita.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="films"></category><category term="wes anderson"></category><category term="design"></category></entry><entry><title>Quick poster I'd probably regret later</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/quick-poster-id-probably-regret-later/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-24T07:26:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-24:2016/08/quick-poster-id-probably-regret-later/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Sapiosexual" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/sapio-poster.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quick, dirty, and thrown together in a couple of minutes. NOT aimed at anyone
or any gender, okay? 😜&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brain vector by &lt;a href="https://thenounproject.com/term/brain/449421"&gt;Clockwise, via Noun Project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="people"></category><category term="sinhala"></category><category term="sexuality"></category><category term="design"></category></entry><entry><title>And So It Began</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/and-so-it-began/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-21T14:06:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-21:2016/08/and-so-it-began/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Backprop" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/backprop.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neural Networks exam in a week!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today's AA exam went much better than expected, given how little I studied for 
it. That kinda thing totally incentivises the wrong kind of behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What to do. I'll start with the (overdue) assignments and try to understand as
much of the &lt;em&gt;mind-boggling&lt;/em&gt; math as I can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And perhaps some day, I'd be able to do something cool like &lt;a href="http://science.sciencemag.org/content/353/6301/790"&gt;these guys&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reliable data on economic livelihoods remain scarce in the developing world, 
hampering efforts to study these outcomes and to design policies that improve 
them. Here we demonstrate an accurate, inexpensive, and scalable method for 
estimating consumption expenditure and asset wealth from high-resolution 
satellite imagery. Using survey and satellite data from five African 
countries—Nigeria, Tanzania, Uganda, Malawi, and Rwanda—we show how a 
convolutional neural network can be trained to identify image features that can 
explain up to 75% of the variation in local-level economic outcomes. Our method, 
which requires only publicly available data, could transform efforts to track 
and target poverty in developing countries. It also demonstrates how powerful 
machine learning techniques can be applied in a setting with limited training 
data, suggesting broad potential application across many scientific domains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="uni"></category></entry><entry><title>Alan Moore on Conspiracy Theories</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/alan-moore/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-19T18:38:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-19:2016/08/alan-moore/</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main thing that I learned about conspiracy theory is that conspiracy 
theorists actually believe in a conspiracy because that is more comforting. The 
truth of the world is that it is chaotic. The truth is, that it is not the 
Jewish banking conspiracy or the grey aliens or the 12 foot reptiloids from 
another dimension that are in control. The truth is more frightening, nobody is 
in control. The world is rudderless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Alan_Moore"&gt;&lt;em&gt;"The Mindscape of Alan Moore" (2003)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="geopolitics"></category></entry><entry><title>කාලෙකින් හෙළ බසින්: චීන නිල මුද්‍රා</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/chinese-wax-seals/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-17T19:23:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-17:2016/08/chinese-wax-seals/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;අන්තිමට සිංහලෙන් පෝස්ටුවක් ලිව්ව කාලයක් මතක නෑ. ඇත්තටම කිව්වොත් 
&lt;a href="http://askubuntu.com/questions/459349/sinhala-unicode-wijesekara-keyboard-in-ibus-on-ubuntu-14-04-not-working"&gt;උබුන්ටු 16.04 දැම්මට පස්සෙ iBus එක හදාගත්තෙ&lt;/a&gt; අද.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;වෙනදටනං මොනාහරි බෙදාගන්න ලින්ක් එකක් හරි තියෙනවනෙ. අද එහෙම 
එකක් නෑ, හැබැයි පහුගිය දවසක reddit එකේ AskHistorians (ඉතිහාසඥයන්ගෙන් 
අසමු) සමූහයේ දැකපු අපූරු පෝස්ටුවක් ගැන කියන්නයි මම යන්නෙ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AskHistorians/comments/4xqfs0/how_were_wax_seals_and_such_not_counterfeited/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;How were wax seals and such not counterfeited?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;චීනය, ජපානය ඇතුළු පෙරදිග රටවල් වල අධිරාජ්‍යවරු භාවිත කරපු මේ නිල 
මුද්‍රා ව්‍යාජ ලෙස පිටපත් කරන්න තිබුනු ප්‍රධානම බාදකය මේවගෙ තියෙන 
තියුණු අඩුපාඩුකම්ලු. මීට හේතුව මේව අතින් නිර්මාණය වීමයි.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Han Imperial Seal" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/han-seal.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;හැබැයි පුදුමසහගතම දේ තමයි අද වෙන තුරුත් පෙරදිග ලෝකෙ එදිනෙදා කටයුතු 
වලට මේ මුද්‍රා භාවිත වෙනවලු. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even today, you can't sign a lease or buy a car/motorcycle or open a bank 
account without one (at least in Taiwan, Japan, Korea, with some exceptions). 
People mostly consider them more secure than a signature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;තව:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When selling a car or setting up a bank account, you need to not only stamp 
the papers, but also bring a paper from city hall certifying your stamp being 
legit (when you get a new stamp you bring it to city hall, so they have a kind 
of master copy).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;කවදාවත් වුවමනාවකට හරියට අත්සනක් ගහගන්න බැරි අපි වගේ අයටනම් මේක 
කියාපු විසඳුමක්.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="sinhala"></category></entry><entry><title>Thoughts on the "Silent Vigil"</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/silent-vigil/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-16T05:19:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-16:2016/08/silent-vigil/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There's been some &lt;a href="https://facebook.com/BBCSinhala/videos/677749315716153/"&gt;"anti-racist" vigil out of nowhere&lt;/a&gt; and there was, as 
usual, a confrontation with one of the "ultra-nationalist" orgs. Without writing 
any further about any of this, I will defer to the wisdom of the crowds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Vigil Comments" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/vigil-comments.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="conflict"></category><category term="people"></category><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Status Update: Mid-August</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/mid-august-update/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-11T20:23:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-11:2016/08/mid-august-update/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We are bound by all the rest&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Like the same phone number&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All the same friends&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And the same address&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I watched &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fr_6qMM_kU8"&gt;Casey Neistat repair a chair&lt;/a&gt; to get over the boredom of 
jury duty and having nothing productive to do all day. He got a 90 minute lunch 
break, and he. built. something. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kinda makes you feel useless when you waste whole days doing nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, I have been wasting days. That was what the whole &lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/thoughts-on-the-mind/"&gt;"loud accusations 
of betrayal directed at my mind" episode&lt;/a&gt; was about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been working on an &lt;a href="http://electron.atom.io/"&gt;Electron&lt;/a&gt; app on the side though, to get familiar 
with the thing. I like it so far, very neat and I get to use React and all the
rest of it. Will release the code on Github if it ever starts doing what I want 
it to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm working on an algorithms presentation for uni and freaking out right now. 
Progress has been slow and the availability of the internet hasn't been helping:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;         day         rx      |     tx      |    total    |   avg. rate
     ------------------------+-------------+-------------+---------------
     08/07/2016     2.33 GiB |  165.41 MiB |    2.49 GiB |  241.70 kbit/s
     08/08/2016     1.50 GiB |  155.75 MiB |    1.65 GiB |  159.95 kbit/s
     08/09/2016   691.81 MiB |   76.57 MiB |  768.38 MiB |   72.85 kbit/s
     08/10/2016     1.18 GiB |  117.25 MiB |    1.30 GiB |  125.89 kbit/s
     08/11/2016   763.70 MiB |   82.37 MiB |  846.07 MiB |  101.63 kbit/s
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I planned to make short posts on this blog with a bit of a longer submission 
statement (more than one quote, some thoughts added in) than Facebook whenever 
I wanted to share a link, but I haven't been using it in such a way. I should 
start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finishing off with a photo I took on the way back from Matara last week, on the
expressway. It was shot from a moving car, through a window with a filter on it,
and looks terrible in true colour. But grayscale saved it and it has become one
of my favourite shots of clouds I've ever taken, and I love taking pictures of
clouds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BIpGuozjQFV/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Clouds on the Expressway" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/bw-clouds.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="work"></category><category term="uni"></category><category term="casey neistat"></category></entry><entry><title>Some Quick Thoughts: The Mind</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/08/thoughts-on-the-mind/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-09T07:15:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-08-09:2016/08/thoughts-on-the-mind/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The mind is a fascinating thing that is little understood and often ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We believe we have mastered it like we've mastered walking, or playing an 
instrument, or typing, or speech. But it is fundamentally uncontrollable and 
has a "mind of its own". Har har.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making the fundamental error of announcing your plans before you implement them
can cause your brain to reward you before you've accomplished anything, and 
therefore leads you to &lt;a href="http://berkeleysciencereview.com/when-telling-others-about-your-goals-compromises-them/"&gt;not accomplish those plans at all&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research conducted by Peter Gollwitzer has shown that individuals feel closer 
to having achieved their identity goals when their identity-relevant activities 
(e.g., attending medical school) are noticed by others. On the basis of this 
work, Gollwitzer and his colleagues hypothesized that even if others notice 
only our plans for identity-relevant activities, we might also feel closer to 
having achieved our identity goals. Because we then feel closer to having 
achieved our identity goals, we may feel less of a need to actually enact those 
behaviours&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm finding out first hand how frustrating this can be, at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="people"></category><category term="biology"></category></entry><entry><title>The month of Augustus</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/the-month-of-augustus/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-31T22:41:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-31:2016/07/the-month-of-augustus/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It begins tomorrow, and I'm really excited because I've been FUP'd by SLT for
the last few days. It's been painful going, as &lt;code&gt;vnstat&lt;/code&gt; attests:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;         day         rx      |     tx      |    total    |   avg. rate
     ------------------------+-------------+-------------+---------------
     07/22/2016   410.55 MiB |   54.48 MiB |  465.03 MiB |   44.09 kbit/s
     07/23/2016   231.05 MiB |   36.32 MiB |  267.37 MiB |   25.35 kbit/s
     07/24/2016   620.32 MiB |   84.95 MiB |  705.27 MiB |   66.87 kbit/s
     07/25/2016   413.00 MiB |   59.05 MiB |  472.05 MiB |   44.76 kbit/s
     07/26/2016   392.72 MiB |   60.14 MiB |  452.86 MiB |   42.94 kbit/s
     07/27/2016   401.44 MiB |   64.09 MiB |  465.52 MiB |   44.14 kbit/s
     07/28/2016   264.50 MiB |   25.76 MiB |  290.27 MiB |   27.52 kbit/s
     07/29/2016   312.83 MiB |   53.04 MiB |  365.88 MiB |   34.69 kbit/s
     07/30/2016   439.92 MiB |   45.89 MiB |  485.80 MiB |   46.06 kbit/s
     07/31/2016   134.91 MiB |   36.42 MiB |  171.32 MiB |   17.74 kbit/s
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been painfully made aware of how heavy Facebook is, when even scrolling
down the timeline for a minute or two and replying to a few messages can cost a
couple dozen MBs. Makes me wonder how I survived on those 1 GB limited SLT
connections back in the day. But back in the day developers cared about  making
their pages light, unlike now. Sigh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been making progress on my thesis (or its lit review, rather). About 3
more papers and I can forward it to my supervisor for a read-through, I feel.
Very much relieved that I've been able to get this far on things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Took a break from studies today (it &lt;em&gt;IS&lt;/em&gt; Sunday) to do some work on &lt;a href="https://github.com/janithl/Kottu2012"&gt;ol' 
Kottu&lt;/a&gt;. Things have been broken a bit since &lt;a href="https://blog.twitter.com/2015/hard-decisions-for-a-sustainable-platform"&gt;Twitter, true to form, 
deprecated useful functionality&lt;/a&gt;. So I got rid of the Twitter share counting,
recalibrated the popularity calculation, and - since I was in there already - 
moved the front-end to use Bootstrap. Because slapping Bootstrap on sites that
have worked perfectly without it is my thing. I'm hoping to deprecate the JQuery 
Mobile-based Kottu Mobile site in favour of the responsive Bootstrap main site 
in the near future, if there aren't any protests and self-immolations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Kottu Desktop" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/kottu-bootstrap-desktop.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Kottu Mobile" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/kottu-bootstrap-mobile.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code&gt;vnstat&lt;/code&gt; output since Aug 1 (this is why I can't have nice things):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;         day         rx      |     tx      |    total    |   avg. rate
     ------------------------+-------------+-------------+---------------
     08/01/2016     1.48 GiB |  133.97 MiB |    1.61 GiB |  156.10 kbit/s
     08/03/2016   305.62 MiB |   44.76 MiB |  350.39 MiB |   33.22 kbit/s
     08/04/2016     1.19 GiB |  115.37 MiB |    1.30 GiB |  126.38 kbit/s
     08/05/2016     1.71 GiB |  174.64 MiB |    1.88 GiB |  182.12 kbit/s
     08/06/2016   603.21 MiB |   53.36 MiB |  656.56 MiB |   62.51 kbit/s
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="code"></category><category term="uni"></category></entry><entry><title>On Unrequited Love</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/on-unrequited-love/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-20T07:45:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-20:2016/07/on-unrequited-love/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Boy oh boy, &lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/shes-wot-m8/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; is something 
I deal with quite often. I rarely have problems with people in my life, because 
I've learned to respect boundaries and not get involved in other people's shit.
But I hopelessly fail sometimes at keeping myself detached from people, and it 
leads to endless suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found this amazing &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Buddhism/comments/2psc9j/my_endless_struggle_with_unrequited_love/"&gt;/r/Buddhism thread&lt;/a&gt; 
this morning that was just perfect, as /r/Buddhism threads often are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout my adolescence and most of my young adulthood I never dated. I used
ideas about attachment and self-reliance as an excuse for not needing to, but
really I just stalled my own development and hurt myself by not finding an
acceptable outlet to express love and practice intimacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hah. So me. "Any relationship I get into will only lead to suffering and 
unskilled behaviour", and all that. The handful of times I've been &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; 
(stretching it, &lt;em&gt;talking&lt;/em&gt;-about-being-with more like) someone, I've been weighed 
down by immense feelings of, for the lack of a better word, Catholic guilt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little over a year ago I saw a girl and was immediately amazed and intrigued
by her. I had the feeling that she was a good friend from my childhood or
someone I had even known from infancy that I was separated from earlier my life.
I doubt this was the case, but it is just the feeling I had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've felt these sorts of connections too, almost sansaric. You find it hard to 
shake the feeling that you're &lt;em&gt;meant&lt;/em&gt; to be with this person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I'm not sure if it was my imagination but I think she had a small crush on
me too because of the way she made extended eye contact and smiled at me
sometimes. But as that happened, I started to feel like it was too good to be
true and I clammed up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aha, as is often the case. Be a douchebag and ignore the girls who take the 
time to talk to you, have no trouble perusing ones that don't give you the time
of day (not really, but the clamming up happens...).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few really good replies that take different approaches at looking at 
the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Buddhism/comments/2psc9j/my_endless_struggle_with_unrequited_love/cmzsv86?context=2"&gt;Altruistic Love&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are attached to someone, you want to be around them because of they 
make you feel good. You enjoy this feeling. It is pleasurable to be loved. What 
this person is to you is, essentially, an object of love. Attachment is about 
self-centered pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you love someone, you want them to experience happiness and pleasure. 
There is no thought of self. If you are the one they are attached to, then 
you want to be near them because it makes them feel good. It is about the giving 
of pleasure, not the receiving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've never seen love and pleasure described in this way before in a Buddhist 
context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people today believe you need a little bit of both. But, from a Buddhist 
perspective, you should love indiscriminately, without attachment to it. And so, 
when it goes away (because it &lt;strong&gt;WILL&lt;/strong&gt; go away... that is the nature of any 
&lt;em&gt;conditioned phenomena&lt;/em&gt;), you are not hurt. This was not about your own pleasure, 
and so you feel no loss. You are not torn from something that pleases you. 
Rather, you recognize that the pleasure that you could once give to this person, 
you no longer can. And that is fine. It is within the nature of a relationship 
for it to end, and so you move forward effortlessly, always giving love 
freely, never attached to it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've often felt that most of my human relationships (about 100% of them 
non-romantic) are about making the other party happy. Whale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Buddhism/comments/2psc9j/my_endless_struggle_with_unrequited_love/cmzpknj"&gt;Right View&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She's an impermanent, flawed person who pees, poops, farts and belches. Seriously, 
take time to visualize this (it's similar to an actual meditation that the Buddha 
taught, in fact he went more hardcore and asks you to imagine her as a decaying 
corpse...yeesh). She's not a goddess, she's human just like you. &lt;strong&gt;She's not the 
answer to your problems&lt;/strong&gt;, she is--and I think the Buddha would agree with this--
&lt;em&gt;just another bundle of problems&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Totally agree on the &lt;em&gt;bundle of problems&lt;/em&gt; bit, and the sort of work that goes into 
maintaining a relationship, and its downsides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you need to practice is a "Middle Way" of self-esteem. The Buddha taught 
that &lt;em&gt;to physically starve and torture yourself will not bring you enlightenment&lt;/em&gt;, 
but neither will pigging out and spoiling yourself with luxury. You need to find 
that middle ground of self-esteem where you believe in yourself enough that you 
feel you do have the power to achieve your goals, but not esteem yourself so much 
that you inflate your sense of self and become egotistical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big take-away for me here is the middle path and how as a layperson I should 
follow it. A lot of my guilt comes from how seeking a partner is basically seeking 
sensual pleasure, but I've never thought about the &lt;em&gt;starving&lt;/em&gt; aspect of it before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find peace and happiness within first, then see if you can relate to others from 
that place of strength first. Otherwise you're just like a druggie looking for a fix, 
not a human being looking to express compassion or true love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Buddhism/comments/2psc9j/my_endless_struggle_with_unrequited_love/cmzpip8"&gt;Pain, and Self-Compassion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best reply in the thread, IMO, came from someone who was "gay and grew up really 
devout Mormon, so I was closeted until the age of 22".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't think the purpose of Buddhist practice is to bring peace, per se. Peace 
is a biproduct of seeing clearly, and clear seeing and learning to stay with our 
emotions seems to me to be the purpose of Buddhist practice. One thing that helps 
me immensely is to see the relationships of close friends. All of them are filled 
with hard work, trials, and quite a bit of suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh god, yes. My rational half hates me for desiring something that I see is causing 
suffering for other people. It's like wanting to try Meth knowing full-well how bad 
it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took a long time for me to see that unrequited love lied to me. It told me 
that if only I could be with my roommate Adam, life would be perfect and beautiful, 
and I would be happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ultimate lie that love tries to sell us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what I also learned was that running away from the pain was not the answer. 
The pain of unrequited love itself contained its own solution. Meditating with the 
fundamental energy of it, I found an incredible tenderness in my pain. I realized 
that it came from years and years of living in the closet and rejecting myself, and 
that &lt;em&gt;the answer wasn't to find someone else to love me&lt;/em&gt;. It was to cultivate loving 
kindness and compassion for &lt;em&gt;myself&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't tried Metta meditation since I was in school, but I'll definitely give it 
a try after reading this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the deep pain still comes and goes--I'm not saying I've found a cure. The 
opposite. Buddhist practice has taught me that there is no cure. And that there's 
also no need for one :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm raw right now from a bit of a painful and sudden (like, this never happens... 
I felt like a teenager again) episode of obsessive affection for someone who 
doesn't even know I like her, and this thread helped me immensely. I hope it helps
you too.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="people"></category><category term="sexuality"></category></entry><entry><title>Where The Lovers Have No Name</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/where-the-lovers-have-no-name/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-18T11:06:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-18:2016/07/where-the-lovers-have-no-name/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Camouflaged Love by Prasad Aluthwattha" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/best-art-ever.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/aluthart/photos/a.1728487060739361.1073741828.1728099647444769/1732564683664932/"&gt;Camouflaged Love by Prasad Aluthwattha&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing I write can do justice to the artwork above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This probably pisses off so many radicals on all sides of Sri Lankan  society,
with their (very similar) views on sexuality and propriety. "Hoo!", I say  to
them, "Hoo!". Roll your morals and your bigotry and stuff it up your arse.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="conflict"></category><category term="prudishness"></category><category term="sexuality"></category></entry><entry><title>Saturdays</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/saturdays/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-16T19:18:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-16:2016/07/saturdays/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All alone, I have cried&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Silent tears full of pride&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In a world made of steel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Made of stone&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturdays are spent at uni, and whenever I'm at uni I think of a 
&lt;a href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/shes-wot-m8.html"&gt;particular person&lt;/a&gt; who 
has nothing whatsoever to even do with uni. At one critical 3 hour paper last
semester, I spent maybe  one and a half hours desperately stuck in an alternate
reality in which we were more than just casual acquaintances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uni takes a heavy toll on my brain as well. Just today, within a couple of
minutes of each other, I had to  grapple with Hopfield Nets, Boltzmann Machines
(and energy functions and my old friend - Bayes' theorem), Convolutional Neural
Networks and their various stages of convolution and max pooling, and - in a 
totally unrelated class - flow networks, max-flow min-cut, to graph colouring 
and its many fascinating applications (all the way from scheduling to Sudoku). 
The only prior exposure I had to any of this was knowing that 4 colours are 
enough to colour any map, because I'm a &lt;em&gt;cartonerd&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, geekery isn't the only reason I &lt;em&gt;enjoy&lt;/em&gt; Saturdays. I get to speak to 3 
peers (who are older and wiser, so not really peers) who give me a fresh 
perspective on a lot of things. This week's installment was on dealing with 
bosses and criticism, and how you need to put your head down and accept things 
as they are and not pick fights. I listened, and pondered, but I don't really 
agree - being the socialist and troublemaker that I am. I think bosses need to 
be smarter at this whole game (and more diplomatic) than their charges, and 
maybe get rid of the whole boss/employee thing altogether and see each other 
as partners (like &lt;em&gt;that'll&lt;/em&gt; ever happen in our deeply hierarchical society).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, an observation my aforementioned peers made a few weeks ago, and I can 
anecdotally confirm because a lot of my batch-mates who graduated with me ended 
up so, is that a significant segment of female Sri Lankan graduates never work
in that field - or work at all. Even in a highly lucrative area like Software
Engineering. They end up married, and apparently that piece of paper is a 
prerequisite. IDK. So the next time someone asks you why there are so few 
female programmers...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="uni"></category></entry><entry><title>Drift</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/drift/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-15T21:33:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-15:2016/07/drift/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Though I know I'll never lose affection&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For people and things that went before&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drift is only natural in human relationships, and you shouldn't really feel bad
about the inevitable. People change, relationships change, you meet new people,
you  move to greener pastures. It's perfectly normal to be mobile in a modern
society. I mean, what  are we? Serfs?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are people I used to spend hours with, at school, online, people with whom
I shared my life and my secrets. And whose secrets I kept. And all these years
later  we barely even keep in touch, which is normal, which is &lt;em&gt;fine&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if only there was a way to get rid of this pesky little thing called guilt.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="people"></category></entry><entry><title>Breathing</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/breathing/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-15T14:15:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-15:2016/07/breathing/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;'Cause I am hanging on every word you say&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And even if you don't want to speak tonight&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That's alright, alright with me...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today's been a bit of an off-day. In the last few days I've a couple of 
interesting Medium posts. Highlights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A healthy product company is, confusingly, one at odds with itself. 
There is a healthy part which is attempting to normalize and to create 
predictability, and there needs to be another part that is tasked with 
building something new that is going to disrupt and eventually destroy 
that normality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failure to create some form of predictability will result in chaos. 
Failure to create some well-maintained Barbaric chaos inside the company 
guarantees that a fast-moving, ambitious, risk-taking and ruthless someone 
else — someone outside the company will invade because they know what you 
forgot: hacking is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@rands/hacking-is-important-ea632819d87c#.5sr0fxo71"&gt;'Hacking is Important'&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve recently moved to a more “hip” location. We used to have personal 
desks, but now we have this “pick whatever spot is avaiable” open area. I 
dislike it a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@Svenskunganka/interviewing-my-mother-a-mainframe-cobol-programmer-c693d40d88f7#.7sslqjnn1"&gt;'Interviewing my mother, a mainframe COBOL programmer'&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Progress has been slow on the research papers I'm supposed to be reading, so 
I picked up watching (the 7th season, which I've missed so far, of) Archer 
instead. I will attempt, today, to print some slides and prepare for the 
lectures I have tomorrow. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I inadvertently opined on some work-related matters (&lt;em&gt;bad me&lt;/em&gt;) because I ran 
into my co-workers yesterday and we engaged in a bit of shop-talk. Whoops. I
just pointed at an &lt;a href="https://www.w3.org/Provider/Style/URI.html"&gt;old standard&lt;/a&gt; 
that I live by and hoped that it wasn't too intrusive of me to get involved. 
Again, &lt;em&gt;bad me&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mal B'day" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/mal-bday.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the reason we all met was: &lt;strong&gt;MALINTHE TURNED 26!&lt;/strong&gt; We're all getting 
really old now, eh? The thing was excellent, though Whight's other patrons 
might've not defined it as such, due to how &lt;em&gt;quiet&lt;/em&gt; our table was. Yes, 
we're always &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; people when we're together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That concludes my useless update for the day, stay tuned for more daily tripe.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="work"></category><category term="uni"></category></entry><entry><title>She's Wot M8?</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/shes-wot-m8/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-14T11:07:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-14:2016/07/shes-wot-m8/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why her though?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She's...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not your type? At all?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; my type, again?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not her&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Come on, dude. I've known you since we had other people wash our bums for us.
She's so not your type&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, we're grown-ups now. Shouldn't we look past "types" and all those
primitive constructs. I like her for who she is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Or you like her who who she makes you...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oh, you know. Saves you from your eternal fear of ending up with a... simpleton&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Look, you barely know her. In the past few days, from what I've seen, you've
been using that blank canvas to project your hopes and dreams&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude. Too much truth on a Monday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;She's your ticket to legitimacy, the girl who reads, and knows, and speaks
well. She's funny, and beautiful, and you know she's going to be on the top of
the world one day. The ultimate Manic Pixie Dream Girl for nerds who actually
want them to be a bit less dreamy and a bit less manic...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I ain't sayin' I'm a gold digger, but I ain't messin' with no...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Look, all I'm saying is that she deserves better than to be blank canvas, or a 
trophy, no? She deserves to be her own woman, and you need to start seeing any 
person you'll be with as an equal, not as a stepping stone for your own...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zip it, Sherlock. I think they've all stopped reading at this point...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ah, it seems so.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="conversations"></category></entry><entry><title>Status Update</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/status-update/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-13T20:56:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-13:2016/07/status-update/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was watching &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KlJnsHpWamU"&gt;one of the talks Casey Neistat gave at
Vidcon&lt;/a&gt; this year, and he talks
about his love for the 'act of creation', and how he loves his job just like  he
loves his family. The drive he has to wake up early to edit a video and put it
out, 365 days a year. It's crazy, and it makes me wish I had the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look, time for some straight talk, which I'm going to go into here because
nobody probably reads this (or knows it even exists). This &lt;em&gt;'sabbatical'&lt;/em&gt; was
going to be me getting down and slogging through a really difficult thesis, in
an area I barely understand (Natural Language Processing, Topic Detection and
Tracking, Temporal Text Mining etc.), and maybe rediscovering the spark, the
excitement that made me want to be a programmer all those years, and which
(along with a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i_2mWhfOhGU"&gt;swelling Oasis
soundtrack&lt;/a&gt;) drove me to create
some really cool side-projects while at uni that ultimately landed me the sweet
gig of being a developer at my current place of employment. And three days in, I
can tell you that motivation is running real low and a huge part of me wants to
step back from the challenge and go back to the mundane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Masters', which I started in Jan 2015, has been harder on me than anything
I've done before. Before, when I was in school or uni, I had 7 days a week and
all of my mindspace to understand what I was being taught and properly digest
it. Contrary to what people expect from me, I'm not a fast learner. I'm slow and
take my time to experiment and truly grasp a concept, before becoming so
familiar and comfortable with it that I can run circles around everyone else
with my newfound toy. Getting thrown toys (and frankly amazing ones at that,
like R or NLTK) and having to balance them with the mundane work I do 9 - 5 on
weekdays has been like missing a WT20 finals because you need to water the
plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, that's the situation as of now. The only driving force I have is this absurd
belief that, since I've finished everything I've &lt;em&gt;'passed'&lt;/em&gt; everything I've
started before, it'll be the same this time around as well. Let's hope lightning
does strike the same place repeatedly.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="uni"></category><category term="oasis"></category><category term="work"></category><category term="casey neistat"></category></entry><entry><title>July</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/july/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-12T23:57:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-12:2016/07/july/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's July, I'm on a twelve week break from &lt;em&gt;jeewanopaya&lt;/em&gt;, it's 
almost midnight and I'm slacking off from doing actual productive
work by checking out static site generators. Pelican seems nice, 
and I've always wanted a hacky, markdown-powered thing for my 
github.io page.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>