<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Janith's Blog</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://janithl.github.io/feeds/personal.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://janithl.github.io/</id><updated>2016-07-15T21:33:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Drift</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/drift.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-15T21:33:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-15:2016/07/drift.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Though I know I'll never lose affection&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For people and things that went before&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drift is only natural in human relationships, and you shouldn't really feel bad
about the inevitable. People change, relationships change, you meet new people,
you  move to greener pastures. It's perfectly normal to be mobile in a modern
society. I mean, what  are we? Serfs?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are people I used to spend hours with, at school, online, people with whom
I shared my life and my secrets. And whose secrets I kept. And all these years
later  we barely even keep in touch, which is normal, which is &lt;em&gt;fine&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if only there was a way to get rid of this pesky little thing called guilt.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="people"></category></entry><entry><title>Breathing</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/breathing.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-15T14:15:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-15:2016/07/breathing.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;'Cause I am hanging on every word you say&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And even if you don't want to speak tonight&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That's alright, alright with me...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today's been a bit of an off-day. In the last few days I've a couple of 
interesting Medium posts. Highlights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A healthy product company is, confusingly, one at odds with itself. 
There is a healthy part which is attempting to normalize and to create 
predictability, and there needs to be another part that is tasked with 
building something new that is going to disrupt and eventually destroy 
that normality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failure to create some form of predictability will result in chaos. 
Failure to create some well-maintained Barbaric chaos inside the company 
guarantees that a fast-moving, ambitious, risk-taking and ruthless someone 
else — someone outside the company will invade because they know what you 
forgot: hacking is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@rands/hacking-is-important-ea632819d87c#.5sr0fxo71"&gt;'Hacking is Important'&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve recently moved to a more “hip” location. We used to have personal 
desks, but now we have this “pick whatever spot is avaiable” open area. I 
dislike it a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@Svenskunganka/interviewing-my-mother-a-mainframe-cobol-programmer-c693d40d88f7#.7sslqjnn1"&gt;'Interviewing my mother, a mainframe COBOL programmer'&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Progress has been slow on the research papers I'm supposed to be reading, so 
I picked up watching (the 7th season, which I've missed so far, of) Archer 
instead. I will attempt, today, to print some slides and prepare for the 
lectures I have tomorrow. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I inadvertently opined on some work-related matters (&lt;em&gt;bad me&lt;/em&gt;) because I ran 
into my co-workers yesterday and we engaged in a bit of shop-talk. Whoops. I
just pointed at an &lt;a href="https://www.w3.org/Provider/Style/URI.html"&gt;old standard&lt;/a&gt; 
that I live by and hoped that it wasn't too intrusive of me to get involved. 
Again, &lt;em&gt;bad me&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mal B'day" src="https://janithl.github.io/images/mal-bday.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the reason we all met was: &lt;strong&gt;MALINTHE TURNED 26!&lt;/strong&gt; We're all getting 
really old now, eh? The thing was excellent, though Whight's other patrons 
might've not defined it as such, due to how &lt;em&gt;quiet&lt;/em&gt; our table was. Yes, 
we're always &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; people when we're together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That concludes my useless update for the day, stay tuned for more daily tripe.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="work"></category><category term="uni"></category></entry><entry><title>She's Wot M8?</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/shes-wot-m8.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-14T11:07:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-14:2016/07/shes-wot-m8.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why her though?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She's...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not your type? At all?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; my type, again?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not her&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Come on, dude. I've known you since we had other people wash our bums for us.
She's so not your type&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, we're grown-ups now. Shouldn't we look past "types" and all those
primitive constructs. I like her for who she is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Or you like her who who she makes you...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oh, you know. Saves you from your eternal fear of ending up with a... simpleton&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Look, you barely know her. In the past few days, from what I've seen, you've
been using that blank canvas to project your hopes and dreams&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude. Too much truth on a Monday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;She's your ticket to legitimacy, the girl who reads, and knows, and speaks
well. She's funny, and beautiful, and you know she's going to be on the top of
the world one day. The ultimate Manic Pixie Dream Girl for nerds who actually
want them to be a bit less dreamy and a bit less manic...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I ain't sayin' I'm a gold digger, but I ain't messin' with no...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Look, all I'm saying is that she deserves better than to be blank canvas, or a 
trophy, no? She deserves to be her own woman, and you need to start seeing any 
person you'll be with as an equal, not as a stepping stone for your own...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zip it, Sherlock. I think they've all stopped reading at this point...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ah, it seems so.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="conversations"></category></entry><entry><title>Status Update</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/status-update.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-13T20:56:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-13:2016/07/status-update.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was watching &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KlJnsHpWamU"&gt;one of the talks Casey Neistat gave at
Vidcon&lt;/a&gt; this year, and he talks
about his love for the 'act of creation', and how he loves his job just like  he
loves his family. The drive he has to wake up early to edit a video and put it
out, 365 days a year. It's crazy, and it makes me wish I had the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look, time for some straight talk, which I'm going to go into here because
nobody probably reads this (or knows it even exists). This &lt;em&gt;'sabbatical'&lt;/em&gt; was
going to be me getting down and slogging through a really difficult thesis, in
an area I barely understand (Natural Language Processing, Topic Detection and
Tracking, Temporal Text Mining etc.), and maybe rediscovering the spark, the
excitement that made me want to be a programmer all those years, and which
(along with a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i_2mWhfOhGU"&gt;swelling Oasis
soundtrack&lt;/a&gt;) drove me to create
some really cool side-projects while at uni that ultimately landed me the sweet
gig of being a developer at my current place of employment. And three days in, I
can tell you that motivation is running real low and a huge part of me wants to
step back from the challenge and go back to the mundane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Masters', which I started in Jan 2015, has been harder on me than anything
I've done before. Before, when I was in school or uni, I had 7 days a week and
all of my mindspace to understand what I was being taught and properly digest
it. Contrary to what people expect from me, I'm not a fast learner. I'm slow and
take my time to experiment and truly grasp a concept, before becoming so
familiar and comfortable with it that I can run circles around everyone else
with my newfound toy. Getting thrown toys (and frankly amazing ones at that,
like R or NLTK) and having to balance them with the mundane work I do 9 - 5 on
weekdays has been like missing a WT20 finals because you need to water the
plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, that's the situation as of now. The only driving force I have is this absurd
belief that, since I've finished everything I've &lt;em&gt;'passed'&lt;/em&gt; everything I've
started before, it'll be the same this time around as well. Let's hope lightning
does strike the same place repeatedly.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="uni"></category><category term="oasis"></category><category term="work"></category></entry><entry><title>July</title><link href="https://janithl.github.io/2016/07/july.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-12T23:57:00+05:30</published><author><name>Janith</name></author><id>tag:janithl.github.io,2016-07-12:2016/07/july.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's July, I'm on a twelve week break from &lt;em&gt;jeewanopaya&lt;/em&gt;, it's 
almost midnight and I'm slacking off from doing actual productive
work by checking out static site generators. Pelican seems nice, 
and I've always wanted a hacky, markdown-powered thing for my 
github.io page.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>